你好 我叫福雷斯 福雷斯甘
Hello. My name's Forrest - Forrest Gump.
要吃巧克力嗎?
Do you want a chocolate?
我能吃掉上百萬塊巧克力
I could eat about a million and a half of these.
我媽媽常說
My mama always said
人生就像一盒各式各樣的巧克力
Life was like a box of chocolates.
你永遠不知道下一塊將會是哪種
You never know what you're going to get.
那雙鞋子一定很舒適
Those must be comfortable shoes.
穿這樣的鞋子你可以走上一整天
I bet you could walk all day in shoes like that
腳都不會痛
and not feel a thing.
我希望能有一雙這樣的鞋子
I wish I had shoes like that.
其實我的腳很痛
My feet hurt .
媽媽常說要想知道一個人的很多事情
Mama always said there's an awful lot
只要看看他穿的鞋就能知道
you can tell about a person by their shoes.
他會往哪堥
Where they're going,
他住在哪
where they've been.
我穿過很多雙鞋子
I've worn lots of shoes.
如果我仔細想的話
I bet if I think about it real hard
我能記得我第一雙鞋子的模樣
I could remember my first pair of shoes.
媽媽說它會帶我到任何地方
Mama said they'd take me anywhere .
她說它是雙魔鞋
She said they was my magic shoes.
好的 福雷斯 張開雙眼
All right, Forrest, Open your eyes now .
你走幾步看看
Let's take a little walk around.
感覺如何？
How do those feel?
他的雙腿很強壯 甘太太
His legs are strong, Mrs. Gump,
是我見過最強壯的
as strong as I've ever seen.
但是他的背象政客一樣彎
But his back's as crooked as a politician.
但我們會讓他再直起來 對吧？
But we're going to straighten him right up, aren't we, Forrest?
福雷斯！
Forrest!
我剛出世時
Now, when I was a baby,
媽用了一位內戰英雄的名字為我取名
Mama named me after the great Civil War hero
內森貝弗福雷斯將軍
General Nathan Bedford Forrest.
她說我們有點親戚關係
She said we was related to him in some way.
他做過的事情是：
What he did was,
建立了一個俱樂部叫三Ｋ黨
he tarted up this club called the Ku Klux Klan.
他們全披著長袍和床單
They'd all dress up in their robes and their bed sheets
看來像一群鬼
and act like a bunch of ghosts or spooks or something.
他們還在馬上也披了床單四處跑
They'd even put bed sheets on their horses and ride around.
不管怎樣 這就是我名字的由來：福雷斯甘
And, anyway, that'show I got my name... Forrest Gump.
媽媽說這名字是提醒我
Mama said the Forrest part was to remind me
我們會經常做一些
that sometimes we all do things that, well,
並沒有意義的事情
that just don't make no sense.
向這邊！
This way. Hold on. Ugh!
好了
All right.
你們在看什麼？
What are y'all staring at?
從來沒有見過
Haven't you ever seen
小孩子戴腳撐的嗎？
a little boy with braces on his legs before ?
不要管其它人
Don't ever let anybody
說他們比你強 福雷斯
tell you they're better than you, Forrest.
如果上帝要讓人人都一樣的話
If God intended everybody to be the same,
他會給每人一雙腳撐
he'd have given us all braces on our legs.
媽媽總有辦法讓我明白她的意思
Mama always had a way of explaining things so I could understand them.
我們住在17號公路附近
We lived about a quarter mile off Route 17,
距離亞拉巴馬州綠茵鎮約半哩
about a half mile from the town of Greenbow, Alabama.
這個地方屬於綠茵縣
That's in the county of Greenbow.
我們的房子來自媽媽的家族
Our house had been in Mama's family
從她爺爺的爺爺的爺爺傳下來的
since her grandpa's grandpa's grandpa
他大概在一千年前飄洋過海來這
had come across the ocean about a thousand years ago.
房子只有我和媽媽住
Since it was just me and Mama
我們有好多空房間
and we had all these empty rooms,
媽媽將這些空房出租
Mama decided to let those rooms out,
給路過的人住
mostly to people passing through,
比如從莫比鎮、或蒙哥馬利鎮來的人
Like from, oh, Mobile, Montgomery, places like that.
我和媽媽靠這個掙到錢
That's how me and Mama got money.
媽媽是個很聰明的女士
Mama was a real smart lady.
記住我說的話,福雷斯
Remember what I told you, Forrest.
你和其它任何人是一樣的
You're no different than anybody else is.
聽清楚了沒有 福雷斯？
Did you hear what I said, Forrest?
你和其它人是一樣的
You're the same as everybody else.
你並沒有什麼不一樣
You are no different.
你的孩子有點不一樣 甘太太
Your boy's...different, Mrs. Gump.
他的智商只有75
His I.Q is 75.
我們都是不一樣的
Well, we're all different,
漢考克先生
Mr. Hancock.
她希望我得到最好的教育
She wanted me to have the finest education
所以她帶我去綠茵縣中心學校
so she took me to the Greenbow County Central School.
我見到了校長什麼的
I met the principal and all.
請你看看這個 甘太太
I want to show you something, Mrs. Gump.
這是正常水平
Now, this is normal.
福雷斯則是在這兒
Forrest is right here .
州政府要求智商起碼要80
The state require s a minimum I.Q of 80
才能上公立學校
to attend public school.
甘太太
Mrs. Gump,
他應該上特殊學校
he's going to have to go to a special school.
在那堨L會很好的
Now, he'll be just fine.
正常水平是什麼意思?
What does normal mean anyway ?
他可能…
He might be...
反應不太靈敏
a bit on the slow side,
但我兒子福雷斯
but my boy Forrest
應該和其它人一樣得到機會
is going to get the same opportunities as everyone else.
他不該去特殊學校
He's not going to some special school
學怎麼翻修輪胎
to learn how to retread tires.
這不過是區區5分的問題
We're talking about five little points here .
一定會有辦法解決的
There must be something can be done.
我們的學校是要排名次的
We're a progressive school system.
我們不想有人拉後腿
We don't want to see anybody left behind.
甘先生在哪兒 甘太太？
Is there a Mr. Gump, Mrs. Gump?
他去度假了
He's on vacation.
你媽媽真是很關心你的教育 孩子
Well, your mama sure does care about your schooling, son.
你不太會說話 是嗎？
You don't say much, do you?
「最後 他必須去試一試
"Finally, he had to try.
「看起來容易 但是…
"It looked easy, but...
「發生了怪事 首先他們…
oh, what happened. First they..."
媽媽 度假是什麼意思？
Mama, what's vacation mean?
度假？
Vacation?
爸爸去哪兒了？
Where Daddy went?
度假就是你去一個地方…
Vacation's when you go somewhere...
然後就不再回來
and you don't ever come back.
總之 我想你可以說
Anyway, I guess you could say
我和媽媽無依無靠
me and Mama was on our own.
但我們不介意
But we didn't mind.
我們的房子總住滿了人
Our house was never empty.
經常是人來人往的
There was always folks coming and going.
開飯！
Supper!
大家來吃晚飯啦！
It's supper, everyone!
這看起來很特別
That sure looks special.
有時有這麼多人和我們一起住
Sometimes, we had so many people staying with us
每個房間都住滿了旅客
that every room was filled, with travelers, you know,
這些人帶著行李箱子
folks living out of their suitcases
還有帽子箱子 還有樣品箱子
and hat cases and sample cases.
福雷斯甘 吃晚飯了！福雷斯？
Forrest Gump, it's suppertime! Forrest?
有一次 又有位年青人和我們住一起
One time, a young man was staying with us,
他帶著一個吉它箱子
and he had him a guitar case.
「你從來逮不到兔子」
# Well, you ain't never caught a rabbit #
「你也不是…」
# And you ain't no #
「我的朋友」
# Friend of mine #
福雷斯
Forrest,
叫你不要打擾這位叔叔
I told you not to bother this nice young man.
不 沒關係 太太
No, that's all right, ma'am.
我在彈吉它給他聽
I was showing him a thing or two on the guitar.
好吧 你可以來吃晚飯了
All right. Supper's ready if y'all want to eat.
行 好極了 謝謝你 太太
Yeah, that sounds good.  Thank you, ma'am.
喂 兄弟 請你再表演一遍剛才那步法
Say, man, show me that crazy little walk you did there .
稍微慢一點
Slow it down some.
「你只不過是…」
# You ain't nothing but... #
我喜歡那吉它
I liked that guitar.
它很好聽
It sounded good.
我伴著音樂移動著腳步
I started moving around to the music,
扭著我的臀部
swinging my hips.
「哭喊不停」
# Cryin' all the time #
那天晚上
This one night,
我和媽媽出去購物
me and Mama was out shopping,
我們路過文斯傢俬商店
and we walked by Vincy's Furniture and Appliance Store,
你猜怎麼著？
and guess what?
「你只不過是一條獵犬」
# You ain't nothin' but a hound dog #
「哭喊不停」
# Cryin' all the time #
「你只不過是一條獵犬」
# You ain't nothin' but a hound dog #
小孩子不能看這個
This is not for children's eyes.
「哭喊不停」
# Cryin' all the time #
幾年以後
Some years later,
聽說v漲鴢茩臛Q人稱為「貓王」
that handsome young man who they called the King,
嗯 他唱的歌實在太多
well, he sung too many songs.
結果他得了心臟病什麼的
Had him self a heart attack or something.
看來「王」確實是不好當啊
It must be hard being a king.
你知道 你的記憶有時清楚得不得了
You know, it's funny how you remember some things,
有時卻什麼也不記得
but some things you can't.
你要開始努力學習了 福雷斯
You do your very best now, Forrest.
我一定會的 媽媽
I sure will, Mama.
我記得第一次乘校車去上學
I remember the bus ride on the first day of school
非常清楚
very well.
你上不上車？
Are you coming along?
媽媽說不要上陌生人的車子
Mama said not to be taking rides from strangers .
這是校車
This is the bus to school.
我是福雷斯…福雷斯甘
I'm Forrest... Forrest Gump.
我是多蘿西哈里斯
I'm Dorothy Harris.
嗯 現在我們不是陌生人了
Well, now we ain't strangers anymore .
這位子有人了
This seat's taken.
有人了
It's taken.
你不准坐這兒
You can't sit here .
你知道 孩子記事實在奇怪
You know, it's funny what a young man recollects,
我不記得我的出生
'cause I don 't remember being born.
我不記得我的第一份聖誕禮物
I don't recall what I got for my first Christmas,
我也不記得
and I don't know
我第一次去野餐
when I went on my first outdoor picnic,
但我卻記得
but I do remember
我第一次聽到最甜的聲音
the first time I heard the sweetest voice
在整個世界上
in the wide world.
你願意的話可以坐這兒
You can sit here if you want.
我一生再沒見過如此美麗的人
I had never seen anything so beautiful in my life.
她就像一位天使
She was like an angel.
你想坐還是不想坐？
Well, are you going to sit down or aren't you?
你的腿怎麼啦？
What's wrong with your legs?
沒什麼 謝謝你
Um, nothing at all, thank you.
我的的腿好得很
My legs are just fine and dandy.
我和她在並排坐在校車
I just sat next to her on that bus
去學校途中我們一直在說話
and had a conversation all the way to school.
當時我的背像個問號那麼彎
My back's crooked like a question mark.
除了媽媽 沒有人和我說話
Next to Mama, no one ever talked to me
或問我問題
or asked me questions.
你是不是有點傻？
Are you stupid or something?
媽媽說 「做傻事的才是傻瓜」
Mama says, "Stupid is as stupid does."
我叫珍妮
I'm Jenny .
我叫福雷斯…福雷斯甘
I'm Forrest... Forrest Gump.
由那天開始 我們經常在一起
From that day on, we was always together.
珍妮和我形影不離
Jenny and me was like peas and carrots.
她教我怎麼爬樹
She taught me how to climb.
快 福雷斯 你能做到
Come on, Forrest, you can do it.
我教她怎麼搖擺
I showed her how to dangle.
「一個好小…」
"A good little..."
她幫我學怎麼認字
She helped me learn how to read,
我教她怎麼倒掛
and I showed her how to swing.
有時 我們就那麼坐著
Sometimes, we'd just sitout
等星星出來
and wait for the stars.
媽媽會擔心我的
Mama's going to worry about me.
再呆一會兒
Just stay a little longer.
不知為什麼 珍妮從來不愛回家
For some reason, Jenny didn 't never want to go home.
好吧 珍妮 我再呆一會兒
O.K.,Jenny, I'll stay .
她是我最好的朋友
She was my most special friend.
我唯一的朋友
My only friend.
媽媽總是對我說
Now, my mama always told me
每天都會有奇蹟
that miracles happen every day
有些人並不同意
Some people don't think so,
但這是真的
but they do.
嗨 傻瓜！
Hey, dummy!
你是啞巴 還是真的是傻瓜？
Are you dumb, or just plain stupid?
喂 我是福雷斯甘
Look, I'm Forrest Gimp.
快跑 福雷斯
Just run away, Forrest.
跑 福雷斯！
Run, Forrest!
快跑！快！
Run away! Hurry!
騎上自行車！
Get the bikes!
我們去捉他！快點！
Let's get him! Come on!
小心點 阿甘！
Look out, Gump!
我們來捉你了！
We're going to get you!
跑 福雷斯 跑！
Run, Forrest, run!
跑 福雷斯！
Run, Forrest!
你給我回來！
Come back here, you!
跑 福雷斯！
Run, Forrest!
跑！
Run!
你現在大概不會相信我的話…
Now, you wouldn't believe if I told you...
但我跑起來像風一樣
but I could run like the wind blows.
從那天開始
From that day on,
如果我要去哪
if I was going somewhere,
我就跑著去
I was running.
那孩子真是個能跑的傻瓜
That boy sure is a running fool.
記不記得我告訴過你
Now, remember how I told you
珍妮總是不愛回家？
that Jenny never seemed to want to go home?
她家的房子和亞拉巴馬州一樣老
She lived in a house that was as old as Alabama.
她五歲時她媽媽就去天堂了
Her mama had gone to heaven when she was 5,
她的爸爸好像是個農夫
and her daddy was some kind of a farmer.
珍妮？
Jenny?
他是個非常有愛心的人
He was a very loving man.
他經常親吻撫摸她和她姐妹
He was always kissing and touching her and her sisters.
後來有一次
And then this one time,
珍妮沒有來乘車去學校
Jenny wasn't on the bus to go to school.
珍妮 你今天怎麼不來學校？
Jenny, why didn't you come to school today?
噓 爸爸正在午睡
Shh. Daddy's taking a nap.
珍妮！
Jenny!
快點！
Come on!
珍妮 你往哪兒跑？
Jenny, where'd you run to?
你最好馬上回來 丫頭！
You better get back here, girl!
你在哪兒？
Where you at?
珍妮！
Jenny!
珍妮 你在哪兒？
Jenny, where you at?
珍妮！
Jenny!
和我一起祈禱 福雷斯
Pray with me, Forrest.
和我一起祈禱
Pray with me.
珍妮！
Jenny!
親愛的上帝 把我變成一隻會飛的鳥吧
Dear God, make me a bird so I can fly far,
飛得越遠越好
far, far away from here .
親愛的上帝 把我變成一隻會飛的鳥吧
Dear God, make me a bird so I can fly far.
媽媽常說上帝是神秘的
Mama always said God is mysterious.
珍妮！
Jenny!
那天他沒有把珍妮變成一隻鳥
He didn 't turn Jenny in to a bird that day.
而是…
Instead,
他叫來了警察
he had the police say
說珍妮再也不必住在那間房子堣F
Jenny didn't have to stay in that house no more.
後來她和她祖母住在一起
She was to live with her grandma,
就是克塈J大街那
just over on Creekmore Avenue,
我很高興 因為她那娷鬻畬a很近
which made me happy, 'cause she was so close.
有時晚上
Some nights,
珍妮會溜出來
Jenny'd sneak out
跑到我的房子
and come on over to my house,
因為她說她很害怕
just'cause she said she was scared.
害怕什麼 我不知道
Scared of what, I don 't know.
我猜是怕她祖母的狗
But I think it was her grandma's dog.
他是只很兇的狗
He was a mean dog.
總之 珍妮和我是最好的朋友
Anyway, Jenny and me was best friends
一直到上中學
all the way up through high school.
嗨 傻瓜！
Hey, stupid!
住手！
Quit it!
跑 福雷斯 跑！
Run, Forrest, run!
你沒聽見嗎 傻瓜？
didn't you hear me, stupid?
跑 福雷斯！
Run, Forrest!
快上卡車！
Get in the truck!
快！他要跑了！快追！
Come on! He's getting away! Move it!
跑 福雷斯！跑！
Run, Forrest! Run!
快追 快追！
Move it! Move it!
你快跑吧！
You better be runnin'!
哇！ - 快！
- Whoo-hoo! - Go!
跑 福雷斯！
Run, Forrest!
一直以來
Now, it used to be
我到哪兒都跑著去
I ran to get where I was going.
我沒想過後來會跑遍所有地方
I never thought it would take me anywhere .
那究竟是什麼人？
Who in the hell is that?
那人叫福雷斯甘 教練
That there is Forrest Gump, Coach.
當地的傻瓜
Just a local idiot.
你能相信嗎？
And can you believe it?
我也能上大學了
I got to go to college, too.
福雷斯 快！
Forrest, move it!
跑！
Run!
好！
O.K. !
跑！
Run!
跑 你這狗娘養的傻瓜！跑！
Run, you stupid son of a bitch! Run!
跑 狗娘養的 跑！快跑！
Run, son of a bitch, run! Go! Run!
跑！跑！
Run! Run! Go!
他大概是狗娘養的最傻的傻瓜
He must be the stupidest son of a bitch alive ,
但他跑得真是快
but he sure is fast.
也許只是我這樣覺得
Now, maybe it's just me,
但大學生活讓我非常迷惑
but college was very confusing times.
聯邦軍隊 執行法庭的判決
Federal troops, enforcing a court order,
今天在亞拉巴馬大學取締種族隔離
integrated the University of Alabama today.
允許兩名黑人進學校
Two Negroes were admitted,
但喬治華萊士州長隨後
but only after Governor George Wallace
發出他的象徵性威脅
had carried out his symbolic threat
站在教學樓門口
to stand in the school house door.
我對於那個聲明…
I take it from that statement...
伊爾 出什麼事了？
Earl, what's going on?
「熊崽」想進這學校
Coons are trying to get into school.
熊崽？如果浣熊想進我家的後院
Coons? When raccoons tried getting on our back porch,
媽媽會用掃帚趕它們走
Mama just chased them off with a broom.
我不是說浣熊 傻瓜 是黑鬼
Not raccoons, you idiot. Niggers.
他們想和我們一起上學校
And they want to go to school with us.
和我們一起？他們？
With us? They do?
在華萊士州長
Shortly after Govern or Wallace
將阻塞校門的威脅付諸實施之後
had carried out his promise to block the door way,
肯尼迪下令國防部使用武力
Kennedy ordered these cretary of defense to use military force.
本台播放的錄像 是當時在現場
Here, by video tape, is the encounter
國民警衛隊指揮官格拉漢將軍
by General Graham, commander of the National Guard,
和華萊士州長的衝突
and Governor Wallace.
因為國民警衛隊
Because these National Guardsmen
今天是作為亞拉巴馬州的聯邦士兵
are here today as federal soldiers for Alabama,
他們住在本州境內
and they live within our borders.
他們是我們的兄弟
They are our brothers.
我們已經獲得勝利
We are winning in this fight,
因為我們喚醒了美國人民
because we are awakening the American people
去面對我們談論已久的危機
to the dangers that we have spoken about so many times
今天的事清楚地顯示…
that is so evident today...
我們的國家正在走向軍事獨裁
A trend toward military dictatorship in this country.
就這樣 當天傍晚
And so, at day's end,
在圖卡盧沙的亞拉巴馬大學的隔離被取締
the University of Alabama in Tuscaloosa had been desegregated,
學生傑米胡和費文馬隆
and students Jimmy Hood and Vivian Malone
已登記參加夏季的課程學習
had been signed up for summer classes.
太太 你的書掉了
Ma'am, you dropped your book.
太太
Ma'am.
華萊士州長說到做到
Govern or Wallace did what he promised.
在圖卡盧沙的校園 他讓人們…
By being on the Tuscaloosa campus, he kept the mob...
喂 那是阿甘吧？
Say, wasn't that Gump?
不 不會的
Naw, that couldn't be.
絕對是他
It sure as hell was.
幾年之後
A few years later,
教學樓門口那位壞脾氣的小個子
that angry little man at the school house door
覺得去競選總統是個好主意
thought it'd be a good idea and ran for president.
但有人覺得不是
But somebody thought that it wasn't.
但他沒有死
But he didn't die.
我的車到了
My bus is here .
這是9路車嗎？
Is it the number 9?
不 這是4路車
No, it's the number 4.
很高興和你聊天
It was nice talking to you.
我還記得那時候
I remember when that happened,
當華萊士遇刺時
when Wallace got shot.
我還在上大學
I was in college.
你上的是女子大學
Did you go to a girls' college
還是男女都有的大學？
or a girls' and boys' together college?
男女都有
It was coed.
珍妮上的大學我不能去上
'Cause Jenny went to a college I couldn't go to.
那是所女孩子讀的大學
It was a college just for girls.
但我一有機會就去看她
But I'd go and visit her every chance I got.
「我不知道我為何愛你」
#I don't know why I love you#
「可我就是愛」
# But I do #
「我不知道我為何哭泣」
#I don't know why I cry so #
「可我就是哭」
# But I do #
「我只知道我知道…」
#I only know I know that... #
很痛
That hurts.
「可我不知道我為何愛你」
# But I don't know why I love you#
「可我就是愛」
# But I do #
福雷斯！
Forrest!
福雷斯 住手！
Forrest, stop it!
住手！
Stop it!
你幹什麼？
What are you doing?
他在傷害你
He was hurting you.
不 他沒有！
No, he wasn't!
往那邊走！
Get over there !
比利 對不起
Billy, I'm sorry.
請離我遠一點
Just keep away from me.
不要這樣…不要走
Don't be such... Don't go.
比利 等一下
Billy, wait a second.
他不懂事
He doesn't know any better.
福雷斯 你為什麼那樣做？
Forrest, why'd you do that?
我給你帶了巧克力來
I brought you some chocolate.
對不起
I'm sorry.
現在我要回我的學校了
I'll go back to my college now .
福雷斯…
Forrest...
瞧你
Look at you.
來吧
Come on.
這是你自己的房間嗎？
Is this your own room?
噓！
Shh!
你有過夢想嗎 福雷斯…
Do you ever dream, Forrest...
夢想你將來要成為什麼人？
about who you're going to be?
我將來要成為什麼人？
Who I'm going to be?
對
Yeah.
我將來不能做我自己了嗎？
Aren't I going to be me?
你永遠都會是你
You'll always be you,
但會是另一種人
just another kind of you.
你明白嗎？
You know?
我想成名
I want to be famous.
我想當個瓊貝茲那樣的歌手
I want to be a singer like Joan Baez.
我只想…
I just want to be...
站在空曠的舞台上
on an empty stage
伴著我的吉它 我的歌聲
with my guitar, my voice.
只有我自己
Just me.
我想自己去接觸大眾
And I want to reach people on a personal level.
我想能夠談一些事
I want to be able to say things,
只是兩個人之間
just one to one.
你有和女孩子一起過嗎 福雷斯？
Have you ever been with a girl, Forrest?
我和她們坐一起
I sit next to them
在家政課的課堂上
in my home economics class all the time.
啊 對不起
Oh, I'm sorry.
沒關係
It's O.K.
對不起
Sorry.
沒關係
It's all right.
It's O.K.
啊 我頭暈
Oh, I'm dizzy .
我想你在家政課上沒做過這個吧
I'll bet that never happened in home ec.
沒有
No.
我想我弄髒了你室友的浴袍
I think I ruined your roommate's bathrobe.
我無所謂 反正我不喜歡她
I don't care . I don't like her anyway .
跑！跑！跑！跑！
Run! Run! Run! Run!
跑！跑！跑！跑！跑！跑！
Run! Run! Run! Run! Run! Run!
停！停！停！
Stop! Stop! Stop!
大學生活過得真快
College ran by real fast
因為我美式足球打得太多
'cause I played so much football.
他們還把我弄進一個什麼東西
They even put me on a thing
叫做全美明星隊
called the all-America team
那樣你可以去見
where you get to meet
合眾國的總統
the president of the United States.
肯尼迪總統接見了
President Kennedy met
全美大學足球隊
with the collegiate all-American football team
在橢圓形辦公室
at the Oval Office today .
那堻抴峈漱@點
Now the really good thing
見合眾國的總統的時候
about meeting the president of the United States
是食物
is the food.
他們讓你呆在一個小房間
They put you in this little room
堶惘釦A愛吃或喝任何東西
with just about anything you'd want to eat or drink.
但是 因為第一：
But since, number one,
我不餓但是口渴
I wasn 't hungry but thirsty,
第二 這全是免費的
and number two, they was free,
我大概喝了15瓶汽水
I must have drank me about 15 Dr. Peppers.
入選全美明星隊感覺如何？
How does it feel to be an all-American?
很榮幸 先生
It's an honor, sir.
入選全美明星隊感覺如何？
How does it feel to be an all-American?
很好 先生
Very good, sir.
入選全美明星隊感覺如何？
How does it feel to be an all-American ?
很好 先生
Very good, sir.
祝賀你 你感覺如何？
Congratulations. How do you feel?
我想撒尿
I got to pee.
我聽著他好像說他想撒尿
I believe he said he had to pee.
不久之後,不知什麼原因
Some time later, for noparticular reason,
有人槍殺了這位不錯的年輕總統
somebody shot that nice young president
當時他坐著他的車
when he was riding in his car.
又過了幾年
And a few years after that,
有人又槍殺了他的弟弟
somebody shot his little brother, too,
這次他是在一個酒店的廚房
only he was in a hotel kitchen.
做兄弟可真不容易啊
Must be hard being brothers.
我不明白
I wouldn't know .
福雷斯甘
Forrest Gump.
你相信不相信？
Now can you believe it?
只不過玩了五年足球
After only five years of playing football,
我得到了大學學位
I got a college degree.
祝賀你 孩子
Congratulations, son.
媽媽驕傲極了
Mama was so proud.
福雷斯 我為你驕傲
Forrest, I'm so proud of you.
我替你拿著這個
I'll hold this for you.
祝賀你 孩子
Congratulations, son.
你有沒有考慮過你的未來？
Have you given any thought to your future ?
考慮？
Thought?
你好 我是福雷斯 福雷斯甘
Hello. I'm Forrest. Forrest Gump.
根本沒人會關心
Nobody gives a horse's shit
你叫什麼名字 膿包！
who you are, pus ball!
你還不如低等生物 吃屎的蛆！
You're not even a lowlife , scum-sucking maggot!
你趕快坐到座位上！
Get your maggoty ass on the bus!
你現在到部隊了！
You're in the army now !
有人坐了
Seat's taken.
有人
Taken.
開始我覺得我犯了個錯誤
At first it seemed like I made a mistake.
入伍第一天
It was only my induction day,
我就給罵得狗血噴頭
and I was getting yelled at.
你願意的話可以坐下
Sit down if you want to.
我不知我會遇到誰
I didn't know who I might meet
或他們會問我什麼
or what they might ask.
你有沒有乘過真正的捕蝦船？
You ever been on a real shrimp boat?
沒有
No.
可我乘過一條真正的大捕蝦船
But I been on a real big boat.
我指的是一種專門捕蝦的船
I'm talking about a shrimp catching boat.
我一直都在捕蝦船上幹活
I been working on shrimp boats all my life .
開始是我叔叔的船
I started out on my uncle's boat
那時我大概9歲
when I was about maybe 9.
我剛在考慮自己去買一條船
I was just looking into buying my own boat
然後就應徵入伍了
and got drafted.
我的名字叫本傑明巴弗布魯
My given name is Benjamin Buford Blue.
人們都管我叫布巴
People call me Bubba,
好像個鄉下佬的名字
just like one of them old red neck boys.
很難以置信吧？
Can you believe that?
我叫福雷斯甘
My name's Forrest Gump.
人們都管我叫福雷斯甘
People call me Forrest Gump.
布巴來自亞拉巴州拉巴特灣
So Bubba was from Bayou La Batre, Alabama,
他的媽媽是煮蝦的
and his mama cooked shrimp.
她的媽媽也是煮蝦的
And her mama before her cooked shrimp,
還有她媽媽的媽媽也是煮蝦的
and her mama before her mama cooked shrimp, too.
布巴家的人瞭解所有
Bubba's family knew everything
跟捕蝦有關的事情
there was to know about the shrimping business.
我知道所有
I know everything there is to know
跟捕蝦有關的事情
about the shrimping business.
我自己也準備去捕蝦
I'm going into the shrimping business for myself
等我退伍之後
after I get out of the army.
好的
O.K.
阿甘！
Gump!
你到部隊來幹什麼？
What's your sole purpose in this army?
幹你叫我幹的事 教官！
To do whatever you tell me, Drill Sergeant!
他媽的 阿甘 你他媽的真是個天才
God damn it, Gump, you're a goddamn genius.
這是我聽過的最了不起的回答
That's the most outstanding answer I've ever heard .
你他媽的智商一定有一百六
You must have a goddamn I.Q Of 160.
你他媽的真有天賦 列兵阿甘
You are goddamn gifted, Private Gump.
大家都聽著！
Listen up, people!
不知什麼原因 我很適合當兵
Now for some reason, I fit in the army
就像一對插銷那麼適合
Like one of them round pegs.
真實一點都不苦
It's not really hard.
你只需把你的床鋪好
You just make your bed neat,
記著要站得筆直
remember to stand up straight,
不管回答什麼問題
and always answer every question
都說「是 教官」
with "Yes, Drill Sergeant. "
聽清楚沒有？
Is that clear?
是 教官！
Yes, Drill Sergeant!
你只需要沿著海底拖你的網
What you do is drag your nets along the bottom.
在一個好天氣
On a good day,
你一次就能捕到上百磅的蝦
you can catch over a hundred pounds of shrimp.
如果一切順利
Everything goes all right,
兩個人捕10個小時的蝦
2 men shrimping 10 hours ,
減去你用掉的油費
Less what you spends on gas...
完成了 教官！
Done, Drill Sergeant!
阿甘！
Gump!
為什麼你這麼快就把槍裝好了？
Why did you put that weapon together so quickly?
你叫我這麼做的 教官
You told me to, Drill Sergeant.
耶穌基督啊
Jesus H. Christ.
這是新的連隊紀錄
This is a new company record .
如果不是因為
If it wasn't a waste
我們這兒兵源不足
of a fine enlisted man,
我會推薦你上軍官預備學校 列兵阿甘
I'd recommend you for O.C.S., Private Gump.
有朝一日你會當上將軍！
You're going to be a general someday!
現在把你的槍拆開重裝一遍！
Now disassemble your weapon and continue!
總之 就像我說過的
Anyway, like I was saying,
蝦是海堻怞n的東西
shrimp is the fruit of the sea.
你可以燒它、煮它、烤它
You can barbecue it, boil it, broil it,
烘它、炒它
bake it, saute it.
把它做成串燒蝦、克洛蝦
They's, uh, shrimp kabobs, shrimp creole,
鮮蝦羹、鐵板蝦、油炸蝦
shrimp gumbo, pan fried, deep fried,
脆皮蝦
stir fried.
還有菠蘿蝦
There's pineapple shrimp
檸檬蝦、椰子蝦
and lemon shrimp, coconut shrimp,
胡椒蝦
pepper shrimp,
鮮蝦湯、油燜蝦
shrimp soup, shrimp stew ,
蝦肉色拉
shrimp salad,
土豆蝦
shrimp in potatoes,
蝦肉漢堡包
shrimp burger,
蝦肉三明治
shrimp sandwich.
還有…差不多就這些了
That...That's about it.
軍隊堭艉W有點寂寞
Night time in the army is alonely time.
我們躺在床鋪上
We'd lay there in our bunks,
我會想念我的媽媽
and I'd miss my mama,
我也會想念珍妮
and I'd miss Jenny.
嘿 阿甘
Hey, Gump.
瞧她那對奶子
Get a load of the tits on her.
看起來…
Turns out...
珍妮惹上麻煩了
Jenny had gotten in to some trouble
為了幾張她穿著校服的照片
over some photos of her in her college sweater.
她被開除學籍
And she was thrown out of school.
「我的寶貝在參加女權運動」
# My baby does the hanky panky #
但那也不算壞事
But that wasn't a bad thing,
因為有一位劇院老闆
'cause a man who owns a theater
他在田納西州孟斐斯市
in Memphis, Tennessee,
看了那些照片
saw those photos
就給珍妮一個唱歌的工作
and offered Jenny a job singing in a show.
我一找到機會
The first chance I got,
我就乘車去孟斐斯
I took the bus up to Memphis
去看她表演節目
to see her perform in that show.
那位是安珀 安珀弗蘭
That was Amber, Amber Flame.
請再為她鼓一回掌
Give her a big hand.
接下來的節目你們一定會喜歡
And now, for your listening and viewing pleasure ,
來自加州好萊塢
direct from Hollywood, California,
我們的叛逆美女
our very own beatnik beauty .
讓我們用最熱烈的掌聲
Let's give a big round of applause
歡迎這位美麗的女鮑勃迪倫
to the luscious Bobbie Dylan.
「一個人要走多少路」
# How many roads must a man walk down #
「才能被稱為男子漢？」
# Before you can call him a man? #
「一條船要出幾回海…」
# Yes, and how many seas must the white dove sail #
她的夢想真的實現了
Her dream had come true.
「才能在沙灘上安睡？」
# Before she sleeps in the sand? #
她成了一位民謠歌手
She was a folk singer.
「而到底需要多少次…」
# Yes, and how many times #
「炮火的轟鳴」
# Must the cannon balls fly #
「才能結束戰爭？」
# Before they're forever banned? #
快來點刺激的
Shake it up now.
還是給她一把口琴吧
Somebody get her a harmonica.
「那答案 我的朋友…」
# The answer, my friend #
「…在風中飄」
# Is blowin' in the wind #
這可不是兒童節目袋鼠船長
This ain't Captain Kangaroo.
嘿 甜心 我這埵釭F西要給你
Hey, honey, I got something here for you.
嘿！去你的！
Hey! God damn it!
嘿 你這傻瓜蛋！
Hey, you stupid jerk!
我在唱歌
I'm singing a song here.
波麗 快走！
Polly, get out here!
你閉嘴！
Shut up yourself!
閉嘴！
Just shut up!
福雷斯 你來幹什麼？
Forrest! What are you doing here?
你幹什麼？
What are you doing?
你幹什麼 福雷斯？
What are you doing, Forrest?
放下我！
Let me down!
你不能老是這樣做 福雷斯
You can't keep doing this, Forrest.
你別老是想著要救我
You can't keep trying to rescue me.
他們剛才想抓你
They was trying to grab you.
很多人都想抓我
A lot of people try to grab me.
可是你不能老是這樣做
Just...You can't keep doing this all the time.
我忍不住 我愛你
I can't help it. I love you.
福雷斯…
Forrest...
你不知道什麼是愛
You don't know what love is.
你還記得我們的祈禱嗎 福雷斯？
You remember that time we prayed, Forrest?
我們祈禱上帝把我變成一隻鳥
We prayed for God to turn me into a bird
讓我能飛得遠遠的
so I could fly far away .
是的 我記得
Yes, I do.
你認為我能飛下這座橋嗎？
You think I could fly off this bridge?
你說什麼 珍妮？
What do you mean, Jenny?
沒什麼
Nothing.
我要離開這堣F
I got to get out of here .
等等 珍妮
Wait, Jenny.
福雷斯 你離開我 好嗎？
Forrest, you stay away from me, O.K.?
請你離開我
You stay away from me, please.
我能搭車嗎？
Can I have a ride?
你去哪堙H
Where are you going?
我無所謂
I don't care .
上車吧
Get in the truck.
那麼再見 珍妮
So bye-bye, Jenny.
他們要送我去越南
They sending me to Vietnam.
那是另外一個國家
It's this whole other country.
請再等一會兒
Just hang on a minute.
聽著 你要答應我一件事 好嗎？
Listen, you promise me something, O.K.?
如果你遇到了麻煩
Just if you're ever in trouble,
不要逞能
don't be brave .
你只要跑 好嗎？跑得遠遠的
You just run, O.K.? Just run away .
好吧
O.K.
珍妮
Jenny.
我會經常寫信給你
I'll write you all the time.
就是這樣 她走了
And just like that, she was gone.
你要平平安安地回來
You come back safe to me.
你聽明白了嗎？
Do you hear?
「有的人生下來」
# Some folks are born #
「是為揮舞旗幟」
# Made to wave the flag #
「紅色白色藍色」
# Ooh, they're red, white, and blue #
「樂隊奏起讚歌」
# And when the band plays "Hail To The Chief" #
「他們放著禮炮」
# Ooh, they'll point the cannon at you #
「那不會是我」
# It ain't me #
「我不是高官子弟」
# I ain't no senator's son #
「那不會是我」
# It ain't me #
他們告訴我們
Now they told us
越南完全不一樣
that Vietnam was going to be very different
和美利堅合眾國相比
from the United States of America.
除了啤酒罐和燒烤以外
Except for all the beer cans and barbecues,
的確如此
it was.
嘿 我敢打賭這水堨都是蝦
Hey, I'll bet there's shrimp all in these waters .
他們告訴我越南的蝦最好
They tell me these Vietnams is good shrimp.
等我們贏了這場戰爭
After we win this war
我們就接管所有東西
and we take over everything,
我們可以把美國捕蝦船開過來
we can get American shrimpers out here
在這水堮源
and shrimp these waters .
一天到晚捕蝦 兄弟
Just shrimp all the time, man.
你們是新兵吧
You must be my FNGs.
早上好 長官
Morning, sir.
啊 把你們的手放下
Oh, get your hands down.
不要向我敬禮
Do not salute me.
這一帶有他媽的很多狙擊手
There are goddamn snipers all around this area
最喜歡打軍官
who'd love to grease an officer.
我是丹泰勒中尉 歡迎來弗特排
I'm Lieutenant Dan Taylor. Welcome to Fort Platoon.
你的嘴唇怎麼啦？
What's wrong with your lip?
我天生就是厚嘴唇 長官
I was born with big gums, sir.
嗯 你最好把它吸進去點
Well, you better tuck that in.
不然會碰到地雷線
Gonna get that caught on a trip wire.
你們幾個是哪堣H？
Where are you boys from in the world?
亞拉巴馬 長官！ - 亞拉巴馬 長官！
- Alabama, sir! - Alabama, sir!
你們是雙胞胎？
You twins?
不 我們不是親戚 長官
No. We are not relations, sir.
聽著
Look,
這堛滌禰輒W矩
it's pretty basic here .
你們跟緊我
You stick with me
一邊向其他人學習
and learn from the guys
他們來這國家有段時間了
who've been in country a while,
你們會習慣的
you'll be all right.
士兵有一樣裝備很重要
There is one item of G.I. gear
它關係到你的生死…
that can be the difference between life and death...
襪子
Socks.
底部有襯墊 軍綠色
Cushioned sole, O.D. green.
你要保持雙腳乾燥
Try and keep your feet dry.
我們爬山的時候 要換襪子
When we're out humpin', change your socks
否則停下來的時候
whenever we stop.
湄公河會把你的腳泡爛
The Mekong will eat a grunt's feet
整個腳會掉下來
right off his legs.
西斯中士 見鬼
Sergeant Sims. God damn it,
我叫你去領的繩子呢？
where's that sling rope I said to order?
我寫到申請單上了
I put in the requisitions.
嗯 你叫那幫狗娘養的…
Well, you call those sons of bitches...
丹中尉很瞭解他的下屬
Lieutenant Dan sure knew his stuff.
能做他的下屬我覺得很幸運
I felt real lucky he was my lieutenant.
他來自一個軍人世家
He was from a long, great military tradition.
他家族的人曾經分別參加…
Somebody in his family had fought
並犧牲…
and died
在…
in every...
每一場…
single...
美國的戰爭
American war.
見鬼 抓緊時間
God damn it, kick some ass.
快去做！
Get on it!
我想你可以說
I guess you could say
他很有榮譽感
he had a lot to live up to.
那麼你們幾個是堪薩斯人 是嗎？
So, you boys from Arkansas, huh?
嗯
Well,
我去過那
I been through there.
小石城是個好地方
Little Rock's a fine town.
現在放下裝備
Now, shake down your gear.
去找排軍需官
See the platoon sergeant.
領你要用的東西
Draw what you need for the field.
如果你們幾個餓了
If you boys are hungry,
我們這兒正好在燒牛排
we got steaks burning right over here .
我們排有兩條守則…
Two standing orders in this platoon...
一：保護好你的腳
1... take care of your feet,
二：別做任何傻事
2... try not to do anything stupid,
比如讓你自己被打死
Like getting yourself killed.
我希望我不會令他失望
I sure hope I don't let him down.
我到了這個國家的很多地方
I got to see a lot of the country side.
我們走了很長的路
We would take these real long walks.
「總會有條路」
# There must be some kind of way #
「從這堨X發」
# Out of here #
「小丑ui訴賊」
# Said the joker to the thief #
我們總是在找
And we were always lookin'
一個叫「越共」的傢伙
for this guy named Charlie.
「一切都令人迷惑」
# There's too much confusion #
「我什麼都不相信」
# I can't get no relief #
停下！
Hold it up!
停下 兄弟們！
Hold up, boys!
也不總是很有趣
It wasn't always fun.
丹中尉總是有些奇怪的感覺
Lieutenant Dan was always getting these funny feelings
對於路上的風吹草動
about a rock or a trail or the road,
他會叫我們蹲下 安靜
so he'd tell us to get down, shut up.
蹲下！
Get down!
安靜！
Shut up!
我們都照做
So we did.
我對什麼都不太明白
Now I don't know much about anything,
但我想美國最好的年青人
but I think some of America's best young men
都參加了這場戰爭
served in this war.
那是非尼克斯來的達拉斯
There was Dallas from Phoenix.
克利夫蘭…他來自底特律
Cleveland... he was from Detroit.
嘿 泰克斯
Hey, Tex.
究竟出什麼事了？
What the hell's going on?
泰克斯是…
And Tex was...
嗯 我不記得泰克斯是哪堣H了
Well, I don't remember where Tex come from...
啊 沒事了
Ah, nothing.
第四排 站起來
Fourth platoon, on your feet.
你們10分鐘內趕到河邊
Y'all got 10 clicks to go to that river.
出發
Move out.
一二一！
1, 2! Hup!
齊步走！
Step it up!
那邊好像不錯
Look alive out there .
在越南最好的一點
The good thing about Vietnam
就是總有地方可去
is there was always someplace to go.
小心手雷！
Fire in the hole!
阿甘 搜一下那個洞
Gump, check out that hole.
也總有事情可做
And there was always something to do.
準備好！
Mount'em up!
散開！掩護他！
Spread out! Cover his back!
有一天開始下雨了
One day it started raining,
然後一直不停的下了四個月
and it didn't quit for four months.
我們經歷了各種各樣的雨…
We've been through every kind of rain there is...
象小針樣的雨
little bitty stinging rain
還有傾盆大雨
and big old fat rain,
從側面下的雨
rain that flew in side ways,
有時甚至還有
and sometimes rain even seemed
從下往上的雨
to come straight up from underneath.
連晚上也下雨
Shoot, it even rained at night.
嘿 福雷斯
Hey, Forrest.
嘿 布巴
Hey, Bubba.
我的背靠著你的背
I'm going to lean up against you.
你的背靠著你的背
You lean up against me.
這樣我們睡著的時候
This way we don't have to sleep
頭就不會鑽進泥
with our heads in the mud.
你知道為何我們是好夥伴 福雷斯？
You know why we're a good partnership, Forrest?
因為我們互相照顧
'Cause we be watching out for one another,
就像兄弟一樣
like brothers and stuff.
嘿 福雷斯
Hey, Forrest,
我在考慮一件事
something I been thinking about.
我有個很重要的問題要問你
I got a very important question to ask you.
你想不想
How would you like to go
和我一起去捕蝦？
into the shrimping business with me?
好的
O.K.
兄弟 你聽我說
Man, I tell you what.
我全計畫好了
I got it all figured out, too.
我們捕到的蝦多少磅
So many pounds of shrimp
拿來付買船的貸款
will pay off the boat.
多少磅拿來付油費
So many pounds for gas.
我們住在船上就行
We'll live right on the boat.
這樣就不用付房租
We ain't got to pay no rent.
我們合夥來干
We can just work it together,
全部都對半分
split everything right down the middle.
兄弟 告訴你 五五分成
Man, I'm telling you, 50-50.
還有 福雷斯 蝦可以隨便吃
Hey, Forrest, all the shrimp you can eat.
真是個好主意
That's a fine idea.
布巴的主意真得很好
Bubba did have a fine idea.
我甚至寫信給珍妮
I even wrote Jenny
告訴她這件事情
and told her all about it.
我給她寄信…
I sent her letters...
差不多每天都寄
Not every day, but almost.
告訴她我在做的事
I told her what I was doing
也問她在做些什麼
and asked her what she was doing
告訴她我經常想念她
and told her how I thought about her always.
和我多麼希望
And how I was looking forward
能收到她一封回信
to getting a letter from her
只要她有時間
just as soon as she had the time.
我總是告訴她我很平安
I'd always let her know that I was O. K.
然後我的落款總是「愛你的福雷斯甘」
Then I'd sign each letter "Love, Forrest Gump. "
「有事情正在發生」
# There's somethin' happenin' here #
那一天 我們象平常一樣走著
This one day, we was out walking like always,
然後 忽然之間
and then, just like that,
就像有人關掉天上的水龍頭
somebody turned off the rain,
太陽出來了
and the sun come out.
「我必須小心」
# I got to beware #
有埋伏！
Ambush!
快找掩護！
Take cover!
快把它拿過來 見鬼
Get that pig up here, god damn it!
福雷斯 你沒事吧？
Forrest! You okay?
強手 強手！
Strong-arm, Strong-arm!
嘿！有個人倒下了！
Hey! We got a man down!
強手 我們是第雷利六號！完畢！
Strong-arm, this is Leg Lima 6! Over!
收到 強手！我們遭到襲擊
Roger, Strong-arm! Be advised we have incoming
在藍點樹林
from the tree line at point blue
從兩個方向！有衝鋒鎗和火箭筒！
plus two! A.K.s and rockets!
我們損失慘重！
We're getting it hard!
啞火！啞火！
Misfire! Misfire!
見鬼！
God damn it!
把那玩意扔掉撤退到樹林！
Get that pig unfucked and on the treeline!
他們壓住我們了
They got us, and it hurt.
我們準備撤退
We're going to move back to the blue line.
撤退！撤退！
Pull back! Pull back!
福雷斯！跑 福雷斯！
Forrest! Run, Forrest!
撤退！
Pull back!
跑！跑 兄弟！
Run! Run, man!
跑！
Run!
撤退 阿甘！
Pull back, Gump!
跑 見鬼！跑！
Run, God damn it! Run!
我一直跑 就像珍妮要我做的
I ran and ran just like Jenny told me to.
我跑得這麼快這麼遠
I ran so far so fast
很快就只剩下我一個人
that pretty soon I was all by myself,
這下糟糕了
which was a bad thing.
布巴
Bubba.
布巴是我最好的朋友
Bubba was my best good friend.
我要保證他沒事
I had to make sure he was O.K.
你在哪兒？
Where the hell are you?
布巴！
Bubba!
我回去找布巴途中
And on my way back to find Bubba,
發現有個人躺在地上
well, there was this boy laying on the ground.
泰克斯
Tex.
好了
O.K.
我不能讓他單獨躺在那
I couldn't let him lay there all alone,
他非常害怕
scared the way he was,
所以我扶起他
so I grabbed him up
背他逃出那
and run him out of there.
每次我回去找布巴
Every time I went back looking for Bubba,
總有人在喊：
somebody else was saying,
「救命 福雷斯 救命！」
"Help me, Forrest, help me! "
好了 好了
O.K. Here. Here .
不要怕 兄弟 躺下 你會沒事的
No sweat, man. Lay back. You'll be O.K.
我開始擔心我可能永遠找不到布巴
I started to get scared that I might never find Bubba.
我知道我的處境
I know my position
越來越危險！
is danger close!
這一帶到處都是「越共」
We got Charlie all over this area.
我這兒需要快速的支援 完畢
I got to have those fast movers in here now. Over.
丹中尉 科曼死了！
Lieutenant Dan, Coleman's dead!
我知道他死了！
I know he's dead!
我他媽的整個排全完了！
My whole goddamn platoon is wiped out!
該死的！
God damn it!
你幹什麼？
What are you doing?
你把我放下！
You leave me here!
走開 把我留在這堙I
Get away . Just leave me here!
走開！
Get out!
啊！我說把我留在這兒 該死的！
Aah! God, I said leave me here, God damn it!
雷利 我是強手
Leg Lima, this is Strong-arm.
我們馬上提供快速支援 完畢
Be advised your fast movers are in bound. Over.
突然好像有什麼東西跳起來咬我
Then it felt like something just jumped up and bit me.
啊！什麼東西在咬我！
Aah! Something bit me!
你這狗娘養的！
You son of a bitch!
我不能離開我的排
I can't leave the platoon.
我叫你把我留在那 阿甘
I told you to leave me there, Gump.
丟下我 你自己逃吧！
Forget about me. Get your self out!
你聽到我的話沒有？
Did you hear what I said?
阿甘 見鬼 放下我
Gump, damn it, put me down.
你自己逃吧
Get your ass out of here.
我沒叫你救我出去 去你媽的！
I didn't ask you to pull me out of there, God damn you!
你又要去哪堙H
Where the hell do you think you're going?
去找布巴
To get Bubba.
我已經呼叫空襲了
I got an air strike in bound right now.
他們會把那堿等
They're going to nape the whole area.
留在這堙I這是命令
Stay here! That's an order.
我要找到布巴！
I gotta find Bubba!
福雷斯
Forrest.
布巴
Bubba.
我沒事 福雷斯
I'm O.K., Forrest.
我沒事
I'm O.K.
啊 布巴 不
O-Oh, Bubba, no.
我沒事的
I'll be all right.
行了
Come on.
行了 行了
Come on. Come on.
我沒事 福雷斯
Ugh. I'm O.K., Forrest.
我沒事 我很好
I'm O.K. I'm fine.
炸平那
Top smoke. Get it up there .
如果我知道這將是
If I'd have known this was going to be
我和布巴的最後一次談話
the last time me and Bubba was gonna talk,
我會想些更好的話來說
I'd of thought of something better to say.
嘿 布巴
Hey, Bubba.
嘿 福雷斯
Hey, Forrest.
福雷斯…
Forrest...
出什麼事了？
Why did this happen?
你中彈了
You got shot.
布巴說了一句我永遠不會忘記的話
Then Bubba said something I won't ever forget.
我想回家
I want to go home.
布巴是我最好的好朋友
Bubba was my best good friend.
我還知道
And even I know
好朋友不是那麼容易找到的
that ain't something you can find just around the corner.
布巴想當一個捕蝦船的船長
Bubba was going to be a shrimping boat captain,
但是 他卻死在越南的一條河邊
but instead, he died right there by that river in Vietnam.
我要說的就是這些了
That's all I have to say about that.
那是粒子彈 是嗎？
It was a bullet, wasn't it?
子彈？
A bullet?
跳起來咬你的那個東西
That jumped up and bit you.
啊 對 先生
Oh. Yes, sir.
正好咬在我屁股上
Bit me directly in the but-tocks .
他們說這樣的傷口價值百萬 但…
They said it was a million dollar wound, but...
那些錢大概是被軍隊留著了
the army must keep that money ,
因為那一百萬我至今連半毛錢也沒看見
'cause I still ain't seen a nickel of that million dollars .
屁股受傷的唯一好處
The only good thing about being wounded in the but-tocks
是冰淇淋
is the ice cream.
我能吃多少冰淇淋他們就給我多少
They gave me all the ice cream I could eat.
你猜怎麼著？
And guess what?
我的一位好朋友就在隔壁床上
A good friend of mine was in the bed right next door.
丹中尉 我給你拿冰淇淋來了
Lieutenant Dan, I got you some ice cream.
丹中尉 冰淇淋！
Lieutenant Dan, ice cream!
你該洗澡了 中尉
It's time for your bath, Lieutenant.
哈珀！
Harper!
庫珀
Cooper.
拉森
Larson.
韋斯特
Webster.
阿甘
Gump.
阿甘！
Gump!
我是福雷斯甘
I'm Forrest Gump.
凱利
Kyle.
尼科斯
Nichols.
麥克米爾
McMill.
約翰遜
Johnson.
驚喜 驚喜 驚喜！
Surprise, surprise, surprise!
阿甘 你怎麼能看這種狗屎節目？
Gump, how can you watch that stupid shit?
把它關掉
Turn it off.
你正在收看美軍台
You are tuned to the American forces
越南電視網
Vietnam network.
這是西貢台6頻道
This is channel 6, Saigon.
接得好 阿甘
Good catch, Gump.
你知道怎麼打嗎？
You know how to play this?
來 我教你
Come on. Let me show you.
打乒乓球的關鍵就是
Now, the secret to this game is
無論發生什麼事
no matter what happens,
永遠不要…
never, ever...
把目光離開球
take your eye off the ball.
好吧
All right.
不知為什麼
For some reason,
我天生是打乒乓的料
Ping-Pong came very natural to me.
看見了？
See?
連傻瓜也會打
Any idiot can play .
於是我開始經常打球
So I started playing it all the time.
我打乒乓球
I played Ping-Pong
甚至沒人陪著也能打
even when I didn't have anyone to play Ping-Pong with.
醫院堛漱H
The hospital's people
說我就像下了水的鴨子…
said it made me look like a duck in water...
不管那是什麼意思
Whatever that means.
但連丹中尉也來看我打球
Even Lieutenant Dan would come and watch me play.
我打了這麼多的乒乓球
I played Ping-Pong so much,
連睡覺時也在打
I even played it in my sleep.
現在…
Now...
聽我說
you listen to me.
我們都有自己的命運
We all have a destiny.
沒什麼事是完全偶然的 它總有緣故
Nothing just happens. It's all part of a plan!
我應該和我的士兵一起死在那兒
I should have died out there with my men,
但現在…我只是個他媽的殘廢人
but now...I'm nothing but a god damn cripple,
沒腿的怪物！
a legless freak!
看著我！
Look. Look! Look at me!
你看見沒有？
You see that?
你知不知道
Do you know what it's like
沒有腿是什麼感覺？
not to be able to use your legs?
是 長官 我知道
Y-Y -Yes, sir, I do.
你清楚我的話沒有？
Did you hear what I said?
你害了我！
You cheated me!
我有自己的命運
I had a destiny .
我本該死在戰場上
I was supposed to die in the field
帶著榮譽！
with honor!
那才是我的命運
That was my destiny,
而你…使我得不到它！
and you... cheated me out of it!
你聽明白我的話了嗎 阿甘？
You understand what I'm saying, Gump?
本來不應該是這樣…
This wasn't supposed to happen...
我不應該這樣
Not to me.
我有自己的命運
I had a destiny.
我曾經是…
I was...
中尉軍官…
Lieutenant...
丹泰勒
Dan Taylor.
你仍然是
Y-You still
丹中尉
Lieutenant Dan.
看著我
Look at me.
現在我能做什麼？
What am I going to do now?
列兵阿甘？
PFC Gump?
是 長官！
Yes, sir!
因為你的表現
As you were.
孩子
Son,
你獲得榮譽勳章
you been awarded the Medal of Honor.
你知道嗎 丹中尉？
Guess what, Lieutenant Dan?
他們要給我勳…
They want to give me a med...
太太
Ma'am.
丹中尉怎麼了？
What did they do with Lieutenant Dan?
他們送他回家了
They sent him home.
兩星期後 我離開越南
Two weeks later, I left Vietnam.
典禮已經開始
The ceremony was kicked off
首先是總統的演說
with a can did speech by the president
關於擴大越南戰爭的必要性
regarding the need for further escalation of the war in Vietnam.
約翰遜總統給四名軍人頒發了榮譽勳章
Johnson awarded 4 Medals of Honor to men from each of the armed services.
美國深深地感謝你 孩子
America owes you a debt of gratitude, son.
我知道你受過傷
I understand you were wounded.
你的傷口在哪兒？
Where were you hit?
在屁股上 先生
In the but-tocks, sir.
嗯 那一定很好看
Well, that must be a sight.
我倒想瞧一瞧
I'd kinda like to see that.
「我獻歌給你 羅賓森太太」
# And here's to you, Mrs. Robinson #
「耶穌對你也特別垂青」
#Jesus loves you more than you will know #
「上帝保佑你 羅賓森太太」
# God bless you, please, Mrs. Robinson #
老天 這孩子！
God damn, son!
然後媽媽回酒店休息
After that, Mama went to the hotel to lay down,
我出去在我們的首都隨處走走
so I went out for a walk to see our nation's capital.
希拉堙I我找了獸醫來
Hilary! I got the vets.
你找他們做什麼？
What do you want to do with them?
媽媽就應該休息
It's a good thing Mama was resting,
因為街上人擠得要死
'cause the streets was awful crowded with people
他們來看那些雕像和紀念碑
lookin'at all the statues and monuments,
有些人吵吵嚷嚷的
and some of them people were loud and pushy.
好了 跟著我！
O.K., follow me!
不管去哪 我都要排隊
Everywhere I went, I had to stand in line.
快點
Come on.
走！
Go!
嘿 你這麼做太對了
Hey, you're a good man for doing this.
很好
Good.
好
O.K.
那兒有這麼個人在演講
There was this man giving a little talk.
不知什麼原因
And for some reason,
他身上穿著美國國旗
he was wearing an American flag for a shirt.
他還很愛說「操」…
And he liked to say the "F" word...a lot.
操這個、操那個
"F" this and "F" that.
每次他說「操」
And every time he said the "F" word,
人們不知什麼原因就一陣歡呼
people, for some reason, well, they cheered.
對！對！
Yeah! Yeah!
來 兄弟 上來 兄弟
Come on, man. Come up here, man.
過來 過來
Come on. Come on.
對 你！過來 快！
Yeah, you! Come on. Move, move !
快 我們上去
Go on. Let's get up there .
給我們講講這場戰爭吧 兄弟
Tell us a little bit about the war, man.
越南的戰爭？
The war in Vietnam?
就是這場…
The war in Viet...
…操他媽的越南戰爭！
fucking-nam!
嗯…
Well...
我能說的只有一件事
There was only one thing I could say
關於越南戰爭
about the war in Vietnam.
我能說的只有一件事關於…
There's only one thing I can say about...
越南戰爭
the war in Vietnam.
在越南…
In Vietnam...
你在幹什麼…
What the hell are you do...
我打死你 你這該死的豬頭！
I'll beat your head in, you goddamn oinker!
天那！他究竟是怎麼搞的？
Jesus Christ! What did they do with this?
聽不見！
Can't hear you!
什麼也聽不見
Can't hear anything!
這個…這個！
This...This one!
給我那個！
Give me that!
大聲點！
Speak up!
我要說的就是…
And that's all I have to say
這些
about that.
說得很好 兄弟
That's so right on, man.
你說得很好
You said it all.
你叫什麼名字 兄弟？
What's your name, man?
我叫福雷斯 福雷斯甘
My name is Forrest. Forrest Gump.
福雷斯甘
Forrest Gump.
阿甘! 阿甘!
- Gump! Gump! - Gump!
福雷斯！
Forrest!
珍妮！
Jenny !
福雷斯！
Forrest!
這是我一生中最快樂的時刻
It was the happiest moment of my life.
我和珍妮又能在一起了
Jenny and me were just like peas and carrots again.
她帶我四處逛
She showed me around
介紹她的新朋友給我認識
and even in troduced me to some of her new friends.
拉簾子 兄弟！
Shut that blind, man!
不要靠近窗子
And get your white ass away from that window .
你知不知道我們正在打仗嗎？
Don't you know we in a war here?
他很酷 他是我們自己人
He's cool. He's one of us.
讓我告訴你我們的情況
Let me tell you about us.
我們在此的目的是保護我們的黑人領袖
Our purpose here is to protect our black leaders
免得他們受到白種豬的襲擊
from the racial on slaught of the pig
他們想要傷害我們的黑人領袖
who wishes to brutalize our black leaders ,
強姦我們的女人 摧毀我們黑人社區
rape our women, and destroy our black communities.
這怪人是誰？
Who's the baby killer?
這是我跟你提起過的好朋友
This is my good friend I told you about.
這是福雷斯甘。福雷斯 這是威斯利
This is Forrest Gump. Forrest, this is Wesley .
威斯利和我一起住在伯克利
Wesley and I lived together in Berkeley ,
他是學生民主社團伯克利分部主席
and he's the president of the Berkeley chapter of SDS.
我們是來提供保護與幫助
We are here to offer protection and help
為任何需要我們幫助的人
for all those who need our help,
因為我們 黑豹黨
because we, the Black Panthers ,
是反對越南戰爭的
are against the war in Vietnam.
我們反對任何戰爭
We are against any war
黑人士兵總被送往前線
where black soldiers are sent to the front line
為一個仇恨他們的國家送死
to die for a country that hates them.
我們反對任何派黑人士兵去打仗的戰爭
We are against any war where black soldiers go to fight
這樣會毀掉他們自己的社區
and come to be brutalized and killed in their own communities.
我們反對種族主義和帝國主義行為
We are against these racist and imperial acts...
「我給她一支槍」
# And I gave her the gun #
「我給她一槍」
# I shot her #
福雷斯
Forrest!
停手！
Stop it!
福雷斯！
Forrest!
停手！停手！
Stop it! Stop it!
我不該帶你來這
I shouldn't have brought you here .
我早該知道大家會爭吵！
I should have known it was going to be some bullshit hassle!
他不該打你 珍妮
He should not be hitting you, Jenny.
走吧 福雷斯
Come on, Forrest.
對不起我在你們黑豹黨聚會上打架
Sorry I had a fight in the middle of your Black Panther party .
他不是故意這麼做的
He doesn't mean it when he does things like this.
我永遠也不會傷害你 珍妮
I would never hurt you, Jenny.
我知道你不會,福雷斯
I know you wouldn't, Forrest.
我想成為你的男友
I wanted to be your boy friend.
這件制服不錯 福雷斯
That uniform is a trip, Forrest.
你穿起來很帥
You look handsome in it.
真的
You do.
你知道嗎?
You know what?
什麼?
What?
很開心我們倆能一起到首都來
I'm glad we were here together in our nation's capital.
我也是 福雷斯
Me, too, Forrest.
我們整晚到處逛 我和珍妮
We walked around all night, Jenny and me,
聊天
just talkin'.
她告訴我她所有的旅行
She told me about all the traveling she'd done
她如何發現了新的思想
and how she discovered ways to expand her mind
學習怎樣在和諧中生活…
and learn how to live in harmony...
和諧那地方一定是在我們西邊
which must be out west somewhere,
因為她一路去到了加州
'cause she made it all the way to California.
「去愛另一個人」
# Love one another right now #
有人想去舊金山嗎？
Anybody want to go to San Francisco?
我要去
I'll go.
走啦！
Far out!
這是很特別的一晚
It was a very special night
對於我們倆來說
for the two of us.
我真的不想今晚結束
I didn't want it to end.
希望你不走 珍妮
Wish you wouldn't go, Jenny.
我必須走 福雷斯
I have to, Forrest.
珍妮？
Jenny?
所有的事都亂套了
Things got a little out of hand.
都是因為這場戰爭
It's just this war
還有愛撒謊的約翰遜總統和…
and that lying son of a bitch Johnson and...
我永遠不會傷害你 你知道的
I would never hurt you. You know that.
想知道我怎麼想嗎?
Know what I think?
我想…
I think...
你應該回綠茵鎮的家
you should go home to Greenbow ,
亞拉巴馬！
Alabama!
福雷斯
Forrest,
我們的人生完全不同 你知道
we have very different lives, you know.
我希望你…
I want you...
收下這個
to have this.
福雷斯 我不能接受這個
Forrest, I can't keep this.
我能得到它…
I got it...
都是因為我做了你叫我做的事
just by doing what you told me to do.
你為何對我這麼好？
Why are you so good to me?
你是我的女友
You're my girl.
我永遠都是你的女友
I'll always be your girl.
「什麼都在改變改變改變」
# To everything, turn, turn, turn #
「這是個改變改變改變的季節」
# There is a season, turn, turn, turn #
「為了任何目標而開始的時刻」
# And a time to every purpose #
「在整個世界」
# Under heaven #
就是這樣
And just like that,
他再次離開我的生活
she was gone out of my life again.
這是個人的一小步
That's one small step for man,
人類的一大步
one giant leap for mankind.
我以為我要回越南去
I thought I was going back to Vietnam,
但他們又覺得
but instead they decided
我對付共產黨的最好辦法
the best way for me to fight the Communists
是打乒乓球
was to play Ping-Pong,
於是我接受了一個特別任務
so I was in the special Services,
走遍全國
traveling around the country,
慰勞負傷的老兵 為他們表演
cheering up wounded veterans and showing'em
怎麼打乒乓球
how to play Ping-Pong.
我打得很好 所以幾年後
I was so good that some years later,
軍隊又覺得我應該
the army decided I should be
加入全美乒乓球隊
on the all-American Ping-Pong team.
我們是第一批訪問中國大陸的美國人
We were the first Americans to visit the land of China
大約一百萬年以來
in a million years or something.
有人說世界和平就在我們手中
Somebody said world peace was in our hands,
但我所做的只不過是打乒乓球
but all I did was play Ping-Pong.
回家以後 我成了全國有名的人物
When I got home, I was a national celebrity ,
比袋鼠船長還要有名
famouser even than Captain Kangaroo.
這位就是福雷斯甘
Here he is, Forrest Gump.
在這兒
Right here.
阿甘 請坐
Gump, have a seat.
福雷斯甘 這位是約翰列儂
Forrest Gump, John Lennon.
歡迎你回國
Welcome home.
你能不能告訴我們 嗯
Can you tell us, um,
中國是怎麼樣的？
what was China like?
在中國大陸…
In the land of China...
人們差不多什麼都沒有
people hardly got nothin'at all.
沒有財產？
No possessions?
在中國 他們不去教堂
And in China, they never go to church.
也沒有宗教？
No religion, too?
難以想像
Hard to imagine.
嗯 只要你肯試著想像 迪克
Well, it's easy if you try, Dick.
幾年以後
Some years later,
那位從英格蘭來的好年青人
that nice young man from England
他回家去看他的孩子
was on his way home to see his little boy
半路上在給人簽名
and was signing some autographs.
完全沒什麼原因
For no particular reason at all,
有人槍殺了他
Somebody shot him.
他們給你…
They gave you...
國會榮譽勳章
the congressional Medal of Honor.
啊 是丹中尉
Now, that's Lieutenant Dan.
丹中尉！
Lieutenant Dan!
他們給你…
They gave you...
國會榮譽勳章
the congressional Medal of Honor.
是的 長官。他們是給我了
Yes, sir. They surely did.
他們給你
They gave you,
你這傻瓜
an imbecile,
讓你這白癡上電視
a moron who goes on television
讓你去出醜
and makes a fool out of himself
在整個該死的國家面前
in front of the whole damn country,
國會榮譽勳章
the Congressional Medal of Honor.
是的 長官
Yes, sir.
嗯 真是…真是太妙了！
Well...that... that's just perfect!
嗯 我對此只能說一句話…
Yeah, well, I just got one thing to say to that...
上帝詛咒美國
Goddamn bless America.
啊 天哪
Oh, God, whoa!
啊 天哪！
Ow! Oh! Oh, God!
丹中尉！
Lieutenant Dan!
丹中尉說他住在一家旅館
Lieutenant Dan said he was living in a hotel
因為他沒有腿
and because he didn't have no legs,
他花很多時間練習他們手臂
he spent most of his time exercising his arms.
向右轉 向右！
Make a right. Take a right!
你在紐約做什麼 丹中尉？
What do you do here in New York, Lieutenant Dan?
我在吃政府救濟
I'm living off the government tit.
嗨 你瞎眼了嗎？
Hey, hey, hey, are you blind?
我正在走路！
I'm walking here!
出來！
Ah, get out!
行了 走吧！
Come on. Go, go, go!
我和丹中尉在一起
I stayed with Lieutenant Dan
慶祝假期
and celebrated the holidays.
你們過了美好的一年 快回家吧
You have a great year, and hurry home.
上帝保佑你
God bless you.
你找到耶穌了嗎 阿甘？
Have you found Jesus yet, Gump?
我不知道我應該去找他 長官
I didn't know I was supposed to be looking for Him, sir.
從越南回來的殘廢軍人
That's all these cripples down at the V. A....
他們都這麼說
That's all they ever talk about.
耶穌這個耶穌那個 哈
Jesus this and Jesus that. Ha.
我…找到耶穌了嗎？
Have I...found Jesus?
他們還叫了個牧師來和我聊天
They even had a priest come and talk to me.
他說上帝在聽著
He said God is listening,
但我只能顧到自己
but I have to help myself.
如果我的心能接受耶穌
Now, if I accept Jesus into my heart,
我就可以與他在天國同行
I'll get to walk beside Him in the kingdom of heaven.
你聽到我說的話了嗎？
Did you hear what I said?
同行…
Walk...
與他在天國同行
beside Him in the kingdom of heaven.
嗯…去你媽的
Well...kiss my crippled ass.
上帝在聽著？
God is listening?
全是狗屁
What a crock of shit.
我要上天堂 丹中尉
I'm going to heaven, Lieutenant Dan.
哦？
Oh?
好…
Well...
你去以前…能不能
before you go... why don't you
起身去街角
get your ass down to the corner
幫我再打點酒？
and get us more Ripple?
是 長官
Yes, sir.
我們大概是在
We're at approximately
紐約市45大街溫阿斯特廣場
45th Street in New York City at One Astor Plaza.
這個地方就是…
This is the site of the old...
拉巴特灣有什麼東西？
What the hell is in Bayou La Batre ?
有捕蝦船
Shrimping boats.
捕蝦船？捕蝦船關我什麼事？
Shrimping boats? Who gives a shit about shrimping boats?
我一定要買一條
I got to buy me one
等我有了錢
soon as I have some money .
我在越南答應過布巴的
I promised Bubba in Vietnam
等戰爭結束 我們合夥捕蝦
that as soon as the war was over, we'd be partners.
他當船長 我當大副
He'd be the captain and I'd be his first mate.
但他已經死了 我只好當船長
But now that he's dead, I got to be the captain.
捕蝦船的船長
A shrimp boat captain.
是 長官。要信守諾言 丹中尉
Yes, sir. A promise is a promise, Lieutenant Dan.
你聽聽！
Now hear this!
列兵阿甘
Private Gump here
要當捕蝦船的船長
is gonna be a shrimp boat captain.
嗯 你聽著 吹牛大王
Well, I tell you what, Gilligan.
等你當上捕蝦船的船長那一天
The day that you are a shrimp boat captain,
我就來當你的大副
I will come and be your first mate.
如果你能當捕蝦船的船長
If you're ever a shrimp boat captain,
我就能當宇航員了！
that's the day I'm an astronaut!
阿丹 你說什麼？
Danny, what are you complaining about?
阿丹 你好嗎？
Danny, how you doing, huh?
輪椅先生！
Mr. Hot Wheels!
這是你的朋友嗎？
Who's your friend?
我叫福雷斯 福雷斯甘
My name is Forrest. Forrest Gump.
這是可愛的卡拉
This is cunning Carla
這是長腿的萊諾
and long-Iimbs Lenore .
你去哪兒了 寶貝？
So where you been, baby cakes, huh?
最近一直沒見你
Haven't seen you around lately.
你應該在這兒過聖誕節的
You should have been here for Christmas,
湯米請大伙喝酒
'cause Tommy bought a free round
每人一塊火雞三明治
and gave everybody a turkey sandwich.
嗯 我遇見了…朋友
Well, well, I had, uh... company .
嘿！我們剛剛去過那兒！
Hey! Hey, we was just there!
那好像是時代廣場
That's like Times Square .
你不喜歡過新年嗎？
Don't you just love New Year's?
你能夠重新開始
You can start all over.
每人都有新的機會
Everybody gets a second chance.
很奇怪…
It's funny...
在這歡樂的氣氛中
but in the middle of all that fun,
我想起了珍妮
I began to think about Jenny,
不知她會如何慶祝除夕夜
wondering how she was spending her New Year's night
在加州
out in California.
「你對她不再有愛了嗎？」
# Don't you love her ways? #
「告訴我你的回答」
# Tell me what you say #
「你對她的愛不再瘋狂？」
# Don't you love her madly? #
「不想去見她父親？」
# Want to meet her daddy? #
「你不再愛她的臉龐了嗎？」
# Don't you love her face? #
「你不再愛正在離開的她？」
# Don't you love her as she's walkin' out the door? #
9...8...
7...6...
5...4...
3...2...
1!
新年快樂！
Happy new year!
「怎能忘記舊日朋友」
# Should auld acquaintance be forgot #
「心中能不懷想？」
# And never brought to mind? #
新年快樂 丹中尉！
Happy new year, Lieutenant Dan!
「怎能忘記舊日朋友」
# Should auld acquaintance be forgot #
「友誼地久天長！」
# In days of auld lang syne! #
「我們站到一起」
# Together we stand #
「分開只有失敗」
# Divided we fall #
「大家一起來吧」
# Come on now, people, let's #
「一起生活」
# Get on the ball #
「一起工作」
# And work together #
「來吧 來吧」
# Come on, come on #
「讓我們一起工作」
# Let's work together #
啊！你怎麼搞的 你是傻瓜嗎？
Oh! What are you, stupid or something?
你有什麼毛病？
What's your problem?
他有什麼毛病？
What's his problem?
你把你那玩意丟在戰場上了嗎?
Did you lose your packet in the war or something?
你朋友是不是傻瓜呀？
Is your friend stupid or something?
你說什麼？
What did you say?
我說你朋友是不是傻瓜？
I said is your friend stupid or something?
不許叫他傻瓜！
Don't call him stupid!
嘿 不許推她！
Hey, don't push her!
你閉嘴！
You shut up!
絕對不許叫他傻瓜！
Don't you ever call him stupid!
得啦 寶貝 你幹嘛這麼生氣？
Come on, baby, why you being so upset, huh?
穿讓你那該死的衣服
Get your goddamned clothes
馬上滾你媽的蛋！
and get the hell out of here!
你應該去馬戲團
You should be in a sideshow.
瞧你這慘樣！
You're so pathetic!
馬上滾！
Get out of here!
你這大混蛋！
You big guy!
失敗者 怪物！
Loser. You freak!
啊 不
Oh, no. No.
對不起 我毀了
I'm sorry I ruined
你的新年聚會 丹中尉
your New Year's Eve party, Lieutenant Dan.
她身上有一股煙味
She tastes like cigarettes.
我想丹中尉發現
I guess Lieutenant Dan figured
有些事你是無法改變的
there's some things you just can't change.
他不想被稱為殘廢
He didn't want to be called crippled
就像我不想被稱為傻瓜
just like I didn't want to be called stupid.
新年快樂 阿甘
Happy new year, Gump.
美國乒乓球隊
The U.S. Ping-Pong team
今天與尼克松總統見面…
met with President Nixon today...
你知道吧？
Wouldn't you know it?
幾個月後
A few months later,
他們邀請我和乒乓球隊
they invited me and the Ping-Pong team
去白宮
to visit the White House.
所以我去了…
So I went...
第二次去
again.
並且第二次見到了合眾國的總統
And I met the president of the United States again.
不過這次他們沒有給我們安排
Only this time, they didn't get us rooms
酒店套房
in a real fancy hotel.
你玩得愉快嗎
Are you enjoying yourself
在我們的首都 年輕人？
in our nation's capital, young man?
你住在哪兒？
where are you staying?
埃伯特酒店
It's called the Hotel Ebbott.
啊 不 不。我知道有家更好的酒店
Oh, no, no, no. I know a much nicer hotel.
是新開張的水門酒店 設備很先進
It's brand-new. Very modern.
我會叫人安排你入住的
I'll have my people take care of it.
保安
Security.
是 先生
Yeah. Sir,
你能不能叫人維修人員
you might want to send a maintenance man
去對面辦公室看看
over to that office across the way .
堶捫O不亮
The lights are off
他們大概正在找保險絲盒
and they must be looking for a fuse box ,
因為他們打著手電 把我都照醒了
'cause them flashlights, they're keeping me awake .
好的 先生。我去查一下
O.K., sir. I'll check it out.
謝謝 晚安
Thank you. Good night.
因此…
Therefore...
我將辭去總統職位
I shall resign the presidency
從明天中午起生效
effective at noon tomorrow.
福特副總統
Vice President Ford
將宣誓就任總統
will be sworn in as president
明天此時在這間辦公室
at that hour in this office.
福雷斯甘
Forrest Gump.
是 長官！
Yes, sir!
根據條例
As you were.
我收到你的退役批文
I have your discharge papers.
服役期結束了 孩子
Service is up, son.
是不是說我不能再打乒乓球了？
Does this mean I can't play Ping-Pong no more?
對軍隊來說 是的
For the army, it does.
就這樣
And just like that,
我在合眾國軍隊的生活結束了
my service in the United States Army was over.
所以我回家
So I went home.
我回家了 媽媽
I'm home, Mama.
我知道 我知道
I know. I know .
露西 他來了
Louise, he's here .
當我回家時 我不知道做什麼
Now, when I got home, I had no idea,
但媽媽有很多訪客
but Mama had all sorts of visitors.
我們有客人來訪
We've had all sorts of visitors .
每個人都想要你用他們的乒乓器材
Everybody wants you to use their Ping-Pong stuff.
有個人還留了一張兩萬五的支票
One man even left a check for $25,000
希望你能說：你愛用他們的球拍
if you'd be agree able to saying you like using their paddle.
我只愛用我自己的球拍
I only like using my own paddle.
嗨 露西小姐
Hi, Miss Louise.
嘿 福雷斯
Hey, Forrest.
我知道 可那是兩萬五啊 福雷斯
I know that, but it's $25,000, Forrest.
我想也許你可以試用一段時間
I thought maybe you could hold it for a while,
看看順不順手
see if it grows on you.
媽媽的確說得對
That Mama, she sure was right.
事情總是出乎意料
It's funny how things work out.
我在家沒有待太久
I didn't stay home for long
因為我答應過布巴
because I'd made apromise to Bubba,
我總要信守我的諾言
and I always try to keep my promise,
所以我去了拉巴特灣
so I went on down to Bayou La Batre
去見布巴的家人
to meet Bubba's family.
你是瘋子還是傻瓜？
Are you crazy or just plain stupid?
做傻事的才是傻瓜 布魯太太
Stupid is as stupid does, Mrs. Blue.
我想也是
I guess.
當然
And, of course,
我也去看望了布巴本人
I paid my respect to Bubba himself.
嘿 布巴 是我 福雷斯甘
Hey, Bubba. It's me, Forrest Gump.
我記得你說過的話
I remember everything you said,
我已經安排好了
and I got it all figured out.
我帶來兩萬四千五百六十二塊四毛七分
I'm taking $24,562.47
這是我所有的錢
that I got, that's left
其它錢用來理髮和買新衣服
after a new hair cut and a new suit
還有帶媽媽上街吃了一頓好飯
and took Mama out to a real fancy dinner,
還買了車票 還買了三瓶汽水
and I bought a bus ticket, then three Dr. Peppers.
告訴我
Tell me something.
你是傻瓜嗎？
Are you stupid or something?
做傻事的才是傻瓜 先生
Stupid is as stupid does, sir.
我拿到這些錢是因為我說：
That's what's left after me saying,
「我和全美乒乓球隊在中國時
"When I was in China on the all-America Ping-Pong team,
「我最喜歡打乒乓球…
"I just loved playing Ping-Pong
「用我的菲利奧萊乒乓球拍」
with my Flex-O-Lite Ping-Pong paddle,"
誰都知道這不是真話
which everybody knows isn't true,
但媽媽說它只是一個善意的謊話
but Mama said it was just a little white lie,
它不會傷害任何人
so it wasn't hurting nobody.
總之 剩下的錢我全部用來
So anyway, I'm putting all that
買燃料、繩索和網具
on gas, ropes, and new nets
以及一條全新的捕蝦船
and a brand-new shrimping boat.
布巴告訴過我所有和捕蝦有關的事情
Now Bubba told me everything he knew about shrimping,
但你知道我有什麼發現嗎？
but you know what I found out?
捕蝦很難的
Shrimping is tough.
我只捕到五隻
I only caught five .
再來兩隻 你就能做串燒蝦了
A couple more, you can have yourself a cocktail.
嘿 你有沒有想過該為這條船命名？
Hey, you ever think about naming this old boat?
船沒有名字就沒有好運氣
It's bad luck to have a boat without a name.
我以前從來沒有給船命名
I'd never named a boat before,
我能想起的只有一個名字
but there was only one I could think of,
世界上最美麗的名字
the most beautiful name in the wide world.
「跳跳舞」
# Do a little dance #
「談談情」
# Make a little love #
「度過今晚」
# Get down tonight#
「跳跳舞」
# Do a little dance #
「談談情」
# Make a little love #
「度過今晚」
# Get down tonight#
「度過今晚…」
# Get down tonight... #
我沒聽到珍妮的消息
Now, I hadn't heard from Jenny
已經很久了
in a long while,
但我仍經常想念她
but I thought about her a lot.
不管她在做什麼 我希望她開心
I hoped whatever she was doing made her happy.
「你不能改變那隻小鳥」
# Oh, and the bird you cannot change #
「你不能改變這隻小鳥」
# And this bird you cannot change #
「上天知道我無法改變」
# Lord knows I can't change #
「上天保佑我無法改變」
# Lord, help me, I can't change #
我時刻想念著珍妮
I thought about Jenny all the time.
丹中尉 你來做什麼？
Lieutenant Dan, what are you doing here?
嗯 我想到海中施展拳腳
Well, thought I'd try out my sea legs.
可是你沒有腳了 丹中尉
Well, you ain't got no legs, Lieutenant Dan.
是的 我知道
Yes, I know that.
你寫了封信給我 白癡
You wrote me a letter, you idiot.
好了 福雷斯甘船長
Well, well. Captain Forrest Gump.
我要親眼來看看…
I had to see this for myself...
並且…
and...
我說過如果你能當捕蝦船的船長
I told you if you were ever a shrimp boat captain,
我就來當你的大副
that I'd be your first mate.
所以我來了
Well, here I am.
我是信守諾言的
I'm a man of my word .
好的
O.K.
但你別以為
But don't you be thinking
我會叫你長官
that I'm going to be calling you "sir."
不用 長官
No, sir.
這是我的船
It's my boat.
我覺得如果我們向東開
I have a feeling if we head due east,
我們就會找到蝦 現在左轉
we'll find some shrimp, so take a left.
向左轉！
Take a left!
哪邊？
Which way?
那邊！
Over there!
他們在那邊！
They're over there!
快打舵盤向左
Get on the wheel and take a left.
好的
O.K.
阿甘 你幹什麼？
Gump, what are you doing?
向左轉！
Take a left!
左邊！
Left!
那邊我們會找到蝦的 兄弟！
That's where we're going to find those shrimp, my boy!
那邊我們會找到它們
That's where we'll find them.
還是沒有蝦 丹中尉
Still no shrimp, Lieutenant Dan.
好吧 我弄錯了
O.K., so I was wrong.
嗯 我們怎麼才能找到蝦呢？
Well, how are we going to find them?
也許你可以去禱告
Maybe you should just pray for shrimp.
「所以我們禱告」
# So pray that #
「我在回家路上…」
# I'm homeward bound... #
所以我每個星期天都去教堂
So I went to church every Sunday.
有時丹中尉也來
Sometimes Lieutenant Dan came, too,
雖然他只讓我負責禱告
though I think he left the praying up to me.
沒有蝦
No shrimp.
你那上帝到底在哪兒？
Where the hell's this God of yours?
奇怪的是丹中尉一說這話
It's funny Lieutenant Dan said that
上帝就來了
'cause right then God showed up.
你絕不能弄沉這條船！
You'll never sink this boat!
我當時很害怕
Now, me, I was scared,
但丹中尉 他像是發瘋了
but Lieutenant Dan, he was mad.
來吧！
Come on!
你這算是風暴嗎？
You call this a storm?
來吧 你這狗娘養的！
Come on, you son of a bitch!
咱們來較量一下吧！
It's time for a show down!
你和我！
You and me!
我就在這兒 來捉我吧！
I'm right here! Come and get me!
你絕不能弄沉…
You'll never sink...
這條…
this...
船！
boat!
卡門颶風昨天過境
Hurricane Carmen came through here yesterday,
沿途幾乎摧毀了一切
destroying nearly everything in its path.
沿海的其他城鎮也一樣
And as in other towns up and down the coast,
拉巴特灣的捕蝦業
Bayou La Batre's entire shrimping industry
成為卡門颶風的最大受害者
has fallen victim to Carmen
漁港完全成了廢墟
and has been left in utter ruin.
記者被告知
This reporter has learned,
實際上只有一條捕蝦船
in fact, only one shrimping boat
倖免於難
actually survived the storm.
露西 露西 福雷斯來了
Louise. Louise, there's Forrest.
從此以後 捕蝦就很容易了
After that, shrimping was easy.
「將會有豐厚的回報」
# There will be great bounty #
「我的上帝…」
# Oh, my God... #
因為人們仍然需要蝦
Since people still needed them shrimps
來做蝦串燒和蝦燒烤什麼的
for shrimp cocktails and barbecues and all
而我們的船是唯一剩下的了
and we were the only boat left standing,
他們只能來布巴甘這媔R蝦
Bubba Gump shrimp's what they got.
我們購置了一大堆船
We got a whole bunch of boats.
有12條珍妮號 還有一個大倉庫
12 Jennys, big old warehouse.
我們還訂做了帽子
We even have hats
上面寫著「布巴甘」
that say "Bubba Gump" on them.
布巴甘捕蝦公司
Bubba Gump Shrimp.
這名字家喻戶曉
It's a household name.
等等 小兄弟
Hold on there, boy.
你是說你就是…
Are you telling me you're the owner
布巴捕蝦公司的老闆？
of the Bubba Gump Shrimp Corporation?
對 我們掙了一大堆錢
Yes. We got more money than Davy Crockett.
孩子 我聽過很多牛皮
Boy, I heard some whoppers in my time,
這是最大的一個
but that tops them all.
我們身邊正坐著一個百萬富翁
We were sitting next to a millionaire .
嗯 我覺得那是個很有趣的故事
Well, I thought it was a very lovely story,
你講得真好
and you tell it so well,
非常熱情洋溢
with such enthusiasm.
你想看看丹中尉長什麼樣嗎？
Would you like to see what Lieutenant Dan looks like?
是的 我想看
Yes, I would.
這個就是他
That's him right there .
我再講點關於丹中尉的事
Let me tell you something about Lieutenant Dan.
福雷斯…
Forrest...
我一直還沒謝謝你救我一命
I never thanked you for saving my life .
他從來沒說出來
He never actually said so,
但我想他跟上帝已經講和了
but I think he made his peace with God.
這是17天堬臚G次
For the second time in 17 days,
福特總倖免被刺殺
President Ford escaped possible assassination today.
總部呼叫珍妮一號。總部呼叫珍妮一號
Base to Jenny 1. Base to Jenny 1.
珍妮一號 請說
Jenny 1. Go, Margo.
有福雷斯的電話
Forrest has a phone call.
嗯 你跟他說他遲點再回電話
Yeah, well, you'll have to tell them to call him back.
他現在很忙
He is indisposed at the moment.
他媽媽病了
His mama's sick.
媽媽在哪兒？
Where's Mama?
她在樓上
She's upstairs .
嗨 福雷斯
Hi, Forrest.
明天見
I'll see you tomorrow .
好的
Oh, all right.
你的腿全好了 是嗎 孩子？
Sure got you straightened out, didn't we, boy?
怎麼了 媽媽？
What's the matter, Mama?
我快死了 福雷斯
I'm dying, Forrest.
進來 坐下
Come on in, sit down over here .
為什麼你快死了 媽媽？
Why are you dying, Mama?
我的時候到了
It's my time.
因為我的時候到了
It's just my time.
現在…
Oh, now...
你不用害怕 寶貝
don't you be afraid, sweet heart .
死亡只是生命的一部分
Death is just a part of life .
是我們注定要面對的
Something we're all destined to do.
我並不知道
I didn't know it,
但我注定要做你的媽媽
but I was destined to be your mama.
我就盡力做好
I did the best I could.
你做得很好
You did good.
嗯…我相信你能實現自己的命運
Well...I happen to believe you make your own destiny .
你要憑著上帝所給予的做到最好
You have to do the best with what God gave you.
我的命運是什麼 媽媽？
What's my destiny, Mama?
你要自己去弄明白
You're going to have to figure that out for yourself.
人生就像一盒各式各樣的巧克力
Life is a box of chocolates, Forrest.
你永遠不知道下一塊將會是哪種
You never know what you're going to get.
媽媽總有辦法把事情說清楚
Mama always hada way of explaining things
讓我也能聽明白
so I could understand them.
我會想念你的 福雷斯
I will miss you, Forrest.
她得了癌癥
She had got the cancer
在星期二去世了
and died on a Tuesday.
我給她買了頂新帽子
I bought her a new hat
上面有很多小花
with little flowers on it.
我要說的說是這麼多了
And that's all I have to say about that.
你不是說你在等7路車嗎？
Didn't you say you were waiting for the number 7 bus?
等一下還會有下一班車的
There'll be another one along shortly.
現在因為我成了足球明星和戰爭英雄
Now, because I had been a football star and war hero
以及全國知名的人物和捕蝦船的船長
and national celebrity and a shrimping boat captain
以及大學畢業生
and a college graduate,
亞拉巴馬州綠茵鎮的父老鄉親
the city fathers of Greenbow, Alabama,
決定給我一個好工作
decided to get together and offered me a fine job.
所以我不再回去和丹中尉一起工作了
So I never went back to work for Lieutenant Dan,
但他繼續打理著我們布巴甘公司的財產
though he did take care of my Bubba Gump money.
他替我買了一家賣蘋果的公司的股票
He got me invested in some kind of fruit company.
後有他打電話給我
So then I got a call from him
說我們再也不用擔心沒錢花了
saying we don't have to worry about money no more,
我說：「好啊 又少一件麻煩事」
and I said, "That's good. One less thing."
「我有了新的希望…」
# I've got a new hope... #
媽媽說過財產不用太多
Now Mama said there's only so much fortune
一個人用不了多少
a man really needs,
多餘的錢只是用來炫耀
and the rest is just for showing off.
所以我拿出一大堆
So I gave a whole bunch of it
給四方福音教堂…
to the Four square Gospel Church...
又拿出一大堆給拉巴特灣漁場醫院…
and I gave a whole bunch to the Bayou La Batre Fishing Hospital...
雖然布巴已經死了
and even though Bubba was dead
丹中尉也說我是笨蛋
and Lieutenant Dan said I was nuts,
我還是把布巴那一份給了布巴的媽媽
I gave Bubba's mama Bubba's share.
你猜怎麼著？
You know what?
她再也不用去任何人家的廚房幹活了
She didn't have to work in nobody's kitchen no more.
那感覺真不錯
That smells wonderful.
因為我成了億萬富翁
And 'cause I was a gozillionaire
並且我喜歡幹活
and I liked doing it so much,
我免費幫他們割草
I cut that grass for free.
但到了晚上無事可幹
But at night time when there was nothing to do
房子空空蕩蕩的
and the house was all empty,
我會經常想念珍妮
I'd always think of Jenny.
然後…她就出現了
And then...she was there.
你好 福雷斯
Hello, Forrest.
你好 珍妮
Hello, Jenny .
珍妮回來與我一起住
Jenny came back and stayed with me.
也許因為她沒什麼別的地方可去了
Maybe it was because she had no where else to go,
也許因為她太累了
or maybe it was because she was so tired
因為她總是在睡覺
'cause she went to bed and slept and slept
好像她多年沒睡覺了
like she hadn't slept in years.
有她在家真好
It was wonderful having her home.
每天我們都散步
Every day we'd take a walk,
我不停地跟她說話
and I'd jabber on like a monkey in a tree,
她聽我說乒乓球和捕蝦
and she'd listen about Ping-Ponging and shrimping
還有媽媽去天堂的事
and Mama making a trip up to heaven.
我不停地說
I did all the talking.
珍妮總是很安靜
Jenny most of the time was real quiet.
你怎麼能這麼做？
How could you do this?
有時我想石頭會不夠用
Sometimes I guess there just aren't enough rocks.
我一直不知道她為什麼回來
I never really knew why she came back,
但我不介意
but I didn't care.
就像昔日重來
It was like olden times.
我們又形影不離了
We was like peas and carrots again.
每天我都會採來好看的花
Every day, I'd pick pretty flowers
放在她的房間
and put them in her room for her,
而她給了我人所能得到的最好的禮物
and she gave me the best gift anyone could ever get
在整個世界
in the wide world.
這是最適合跑步的
They're made just for running.
「帶我回家見親朋」
# Carry me home to see my kin #
他還教我如何跳舞
And she even showed me how to dance.
「我又想起老朋友」
#I miss ol'Bammy once again #
「我不再對他不起」
#And I think it's a sin #
「亞拉巴馬我的家…」
# Sweet home Alabama... #
我們就像一家人 珍妮和我…
Well, we was like family, Jenny and me...
那是我一生最快樂的時光
and it was the happiest time in my life.
你看還要看嗎？
You done watching it?
我要去睡了
I'm going to bed.
你能嫁給我嗎？
Will you marry me?
我會做個好丈夫的 珍妮
I'd make a good husband, Jenny.
你會的 福雷斯
You would, Forrest.
但你不能嫁給我
But you won't marry me.
你不願意嫁給我
You don't want to marry me.
你為什麼不愛我 珍妮？
Why don't you love me, Jenny?
我不是很聰明
I'm not a smart man,
但我知道什麼是愛
but I know what love is.
珍妮…
Jenny...
福雷斯 我真的愛你
Forrest, I do love you.
那你為什麼要跑？
Where are you running off to?
我沒有跑
I'm not running.
那一天
That day,
不知什麼原因
for no particular reason,
我決定出去跑一趟
I decided to go for a little run.
所以我跑到路的盡頭
So I ran to the end of the road,
當我到達那 我想也許我能跑到城邊
and when I got there, I thought maybe I'd run to the end of town.
卡特總統因中暑病倒…
President Carter, suffering from heat exhaustion...
而當我到達那
And when I got there,
我想也許我能跑遍綠茵縣
I thought maybe I'd just run across Greenbow County.
這時我想既然我跑了那麼遠
Now, I figured since I'd run this far,
也許我可以跑遍亞拉巴馬州
maybe I'd just run across the great state of Alabama.
我就這麼做了
And that's what I did.
我橫越整個亞拉巴馬
I ran clear across Alabama.
不知什麼原因 我繼續跑
No particular reason. I just kept on going.
我一直跑到大海
I ran clear to the ocean.
當我到達那
And when I got there,
我想既然我跑了那麼遠
I figured since I'd gone this far,
也許不如掉頭繼續跑
might as well turn around, just keep on going.
然後當我跑到另一個大海
And when I got to another ocean,
我想既然我跑了那麼遠…
I figured since I'd gone this far...
我也許不如掉頭
I might as well just turn back
繼續跑下去
and keep right on going.
當我累了 我就睡覺
when I got tired, I slept.
當我餓了 我就吃飯
when I got hungry, I ate.
當我想去…
When I had to go...
你知道…
you know...
我就去
I went.
所以…
And so...
你不停地跑?
you just ran?
對
Yeah.
「看著路在車輪下延伸」
# Lookin' out at the road rushin' under my wheels #
「看著一年年時光飛逝」
# Lookin' back at the years gone by #
「就像一片片夏日農田」
# Like so many summer fields #
「六五年那時我十七歲」
# In '65, I was 17 #
「我在一刻不停地奔跑」
# And runnin' up one on one #
「我不知道跑到了何處」
# I don't know where I'm runnin' now #
「我只是在不停地奔跑」
# I'm just runnin' on #
「奔跑」
# Runnin' on #
「無緣無故地奔跑」
# Runnin' on empty #
「奔跑」
# Runnin' on #
「精疲力竭」
# Runnin' dry #
「奔跑…」
# Runnin' on... #
我想了很多事…
I'd think a lot...
關於媽媽和布巴還有丹中尉
about Mama and Bubba and Lieutenant Dan.
但最經常的
But most of all,
我在想念珍妮
I thought about Jenny.
我非常想念她
I thought about her a lot.
兩年多來
For more than two years,
一位名叫福雷斯甘的人
a man named Forrest Gump,
來自亞拉巴馬綠茵縣的園藝師 除了睡覺
a gardener from Greenbow, Alabama, stopping only to sleep,
就是不停跑步橫越美國
has been running across America.
查爾斯庫珀為你報導
Charles Cooper brings you this report.
他這是第四次
For the fourth time
進行橫越美國的旅程
on his journey across America,
福雷斯甘 來自亞拉巴馬綠茵縣的園藝師
Forrest Gump, the gardener from Greenbow, Alabama,
今天將再次跑過密西西比河
is about to cross the Mississippi River again today.
天那 福雷斯？
I'll be damned. Forrest?
先生 你為什麼要跑？
Sir, where are you running?
你是為了世界和平嗎？
Are you doing this for world peace?
你是為了無家可者嗎？
Are you doing this for the homeless?
你是為了婦女權利嗎？
Are you running for women's rights?
為了保護環境嗎？
The environment?
他們就是不相信
they just couldn't believe
有些人跑步
that Somebody would do all that running
什麼都不為
for no particular reason.
你為什麼這樣做？
Why are you doing this?
我只是想跑
I just felt like running.
I just felt like runnin'.
是你
That's you.
我不敢相信真的是你
I can't believe it's really you.
然後…不知什麼原因
Now...for some reason,
我所做的事好像
what I was doing seemed to...
在某些人看來有了意義
make sense to people.
我的頭腦中好像響起一聲警報
It was like an alarm went off in my head.
我說 「他是個實幹家
I said, "Here's a guy that's got his act together.
他擁有所有問題的答案」
Here's somebody who has the answer."
我要追隨你 甘先生
I'll follow you anywhere, Mr. Gump.
於是我有了夥伴
So I got company.
然後 我有了更多的夥伴
And after that, I got more company.
然後 又有更多的人加入
And then, even more people joined in.
有人後來告訴我
Somebody later told me
人們看到了希望
it gave people hope.
那時…
Now...
那時我什麼也不知道
Now, I don't know anything about that,
有些人曾經問我
but some of those people asked me
我能不能幫助他們
if I could help them out.
我想你也許能夠幫助我
I was wondering if you might help me.
我是做貼紙生意的
I'm in the bumper sticker business.
我需要一句好的口號
I need a good slogan,
你很有天才
and since you've been so inspirational,
我想你也許能幫助我…
I thought you might be able to help me...
啊！你剛跑過…
Whoa, man! You just ran
一大堆狗屎！
through a big pile of dog shit!
不管它
It happens.
什麼 狗屎？
What, shit?
有時
Sometimes.
幾年後 我聽說那個傢伙
And some years later, I heard that that fella
想出來一條貼紙口號
did come up with a bumper sticker slogan
賺了一大筆錢
and made a lot of money off of it.
還有一次 我一個人跑著
Another time, I was running along.
遇到個賣T恤衫賠了本的人
Somebody who'd lost all his money in the T-shirt business,
他希望把我的臉印在T恤衫上
he wanted to put my face on a T-shirt,
但他不太會畫畫
but he couldn't draw that well,
他也沒帶照相機
and he didn't have a camera.
用這個吧 反正沒人喜歡這顏色
Here, use this one. Nobody likes that color anyway.
祝你過得好
Have a nice day.
幾年後 我聽說
Someyears later, I found out
那個人確實想出了一個T恤圖案
that that man did come up with an idea for a T-shirt.
賺了一大筆錢
He made a lot of money.
總之 就像我說過的
Anyway, like I was saying,
我有了很多夥伴
I had a lot of company.
我媽媽總是說
My mama always said,
「你得丟開以往的事
"You got to put the past behind you
「才能不斷繼續前進」
before you can move on. "
我想那就是我這次跑步的意義了
And I think that's what my running was all about.
我跑了三年…
I had run for three years...
兩個月…
two months....
14天又16小時
14 days, and 16 hours.
安靜 安靜。他有話要說
Quiet. Quiet. He's going to say something.
我很累了
I'm pretty tired.
現在我想回家了
Think I'll go home now .
那我們該怎麼辦？
Now what are we supposed to do?
就這樣…
And just like that...
我跑步的日子結束了
my runnin' days was over.
我回到亞拉巴馬的家
So I went home to Alabama.
不久前 下午2時25分
Moments ago, at 2:25 P.M.,
當堮睋`統走出…
as President Reagan was leaving the...
開了五至六槍
Five or six gunshots were fired
一個不知名的兇手
by an unknown, would-be assassin.
總統胸部中彈…
The president was shot in the chest...
我拿到郵件
I picked up the mail.
有一天 天氣晴朗
And one day, out of the blue clear sky,
我收到一封珍妮的來信
I got a letter from Jenny
問我能不能來薩凡納
wondering if I could come down to Savannah
來看她 所以我就來了
and see her, and that's what I'm doing here.
她在電視上看到我…跑步
She saw me on TV... running.
我正要乘9路車去堜_蒙街
I'm supposed to go on the number 9 bus to Richmond Street
然後下車向左走
and get off and go one block left
到亨利街1947號…
to 1947 Henry Street...
4單元
apartment 4.
那你不必乘公交車
Why, you don't need to take a bus.
亨利街離這兒只有五六個街區…
Henry Street is just five or six blocks...
就往那邊
down that way.
往那邊？
Down that way?
往那邊
Down that way .
很高興和你聊天
It was nice talking to you.
我希望你一切順利！
I hope everything works out for you!
福雷斯！
Forrest!
你好嗎？
How you doin'?
進來 進來！
Come in! Come in!
我收到了你的信
I got your letter.
哦 我還正擔心你收不到呢
Oh, I was wondering about that.
這是你住的地方？
This your house?
對 現在很亂
Yeah. It's messy right now.
我剛下班回來
I just got off work.
很好
It's nice.
你還買了空調
You got air-conditioning.
謝謝
Thank you.
我吃了
I ate some.
我 嗯…保存了一本你的剪報和…
I, uh, kept...kept a scrap book of...of your clippings and...
別的東西 給你
everything. There you are.
對 我看見你跑了
Yes, I got you running.
我跑了很長的路
I ran a long way.
很長的時間
It's a long time.
那…
There...
聽我說 福雷斯 我不知該怎麼說
Listen, Forrest, I don't know how to say this.
我…
I just...
我想向你道歉
I want to apologize
為我對你做的一切 因為…
for anything that I ever did to you 'cause...
我做得很糟…
I was messed up...
一直以來 而且…
for a long time, and...
嗨 你好
Hey, you.
這位是我從亞拉巴馬來的老朋友
This is my old friend from Alabama.
你好嗎？
How do you do?
下星期我的日程安排要改了 所以我…
Next week my schedule changes, so I can...
沒問題 我得走了。我沒停車位
No problem. Got to go. I'm double-parked.
好吧 謝謝
O.K. Thanks.
這是我很好的朋友甘先生
This is my very good friend Mr. Gump.
你能問聲好嗎？
Can you say hi?
你好 甘先生
Hello, Mr. Gump.
你好
Hello.
我能去看電視嗎？
Can I go watch TV now?
可以 但聲音輕點
Yes. Just keep it low.
你做媽媽了 珍妮
You're a mama, Jenny.
我做媽媽了
I'm a mama.
他名字叫福雷斯
His name's Forrest.
和我一樣！
Like me!
他的名字和他爸爸一樣
I named him after his daddy.
他的爸爸也叫福雷斯？
He got a daddy named Forrest, too?
你就是他爸爸 福雷斯
You're his daddy, Forrest.
福雷斯 看著我
Forrest, look at me.
看著我 福雷斯
Look at me, Forrest.
你不用擔心
There's nothing you need to do.
你沒有做錯事
You didn't do anything wrong.
好嗎？
O.K.?
他漂亮嗎？
Isn't he beautiful?
他是我見過最漂亮的
He's the most beautiful thing I've ever seen.
可是…
But...
他…他聰明嗎？比如他能不能…
is...is he s-smart? Like, can he...
他非常聰明
He's very smart.
他是他班上最聰明的一個
He's one of the smartest in his class.
沒事的 去和他聊聊吧
Yeah, it's O.K. Go talk to him.
你在看什麼？
What are you watching?
伯特和埃妮
Bert and Ernie.
福雷斯…
Forrest...
我生病了
I'm sick.
什麼 你是不是感冒了
What, do you have a cough due to a cold?
我染上了一種病毒 醫生…
I have some kind of virus, and the doctors,
他們不知道是什麼病毒
they don't know what it is,
他們也不知道如何醫治
and there isn't anything they can do about it.
你和我一起回家吧
You could come home with me.
珍妮 你和…
Jenny, you and...
小福雷斯
little Forrest
一起
could come stay
住到綠茵鎮來
at my house in Greenbow.
要是你病了我會照顧你
I'll take care of you if you're sick.
你願意娶我嗎 福雷斯？
Would you marry me, Forrest?
好的
O.K.
請坐
Please take your seats.
福雷斯？
Forrest?
快開始了
It's time to start.
你的領帶
Your tie.
丹中尉
Lieutenant Dan.
你好 福雷斯
Hello, Forrest.
你有雙新腿了
You got new legs.
新腿！
New legs!
對 我有雙新腿了
Yeah. I got new legs.
是定做的
Custom-made.
鈦合金的
Titanium alloy.
航天飛機也是用它造的
It's what they use on the space shuttle.
魔腿
Magic legs.
這位…
This...
是我的未婚妻
is my fiancee.
蘇珊
Susan.
丹中尉
Lieutenant Dan.
嗨 福雷斯
Hi, Forrest.
丹中尉…
Lieutenant Dan...
這位是我的珍妮
this is my Jenny.
很高興能見到你
Hi. It's nice to meet you finally.
福雷斯 你願意讓珍妮
Do you, Forrest, take Jenny
做你的妻子嗎？
to be your wife?
珍妮 你願意讓福雷斯
Do you, Jenny, take Forrest
做你的丈夫嗎？
to be your husband?
那麼我宣佈你們結為夫妻
And so I pronounce you man and wife.
嘿 福雷斯…
Hey, Forrest...
你在越南害怕過嗎？
were you scared in Vietnam?
是的
Yes.
我…
Well, I...
我不知道
I don't know.
當雨停的時候
Sometimes it would stop raining
有時能看到星星…
long enough for the stars to come out...
那感覺很好
and then it was nice.
就像太陽下山前
It was like just before the sun goes to bed
在拉巴特灣
down on the bayou.
海面的閃閃鱗光…
there was always a million sparkles on the water...
就像山間的湖水
like that mountain lake.
那樣的清澈 珍妮
It was so clear, Jenny,
就像另一片天空
it looked like there were two skies
兩重天空
one on top of the other.
還有在沙漠 當太陽升起…
And then in the desert, when the sun comes up...
我分不清
I couldn't tell
哪兒是天 哪兒是地
where heaven stopped and the earth began.
真是美麗
It's so beautiful.
我但願那時和你在一起
I wish I could've been there with you.
你確實在的
You were.
我愛你
I love you.
你在星期六清晨死去
You died on a Saturday morning.
我把你葬在我們的樹下
And I had you placed here under our tree.
我把你父親的房子
And I had that house of your father's
推成了平地
bulldozed to the ground.
媽媽…
Mama...
總是說…
always said
死亡是生命的一部分
that dyin' was a part of life .
我真的希望不是這樣
I sure wish it wasn't.
小福雷斯…
Little Forrest is...
很好
doing just fine.
「不過…」
"But..."
就要去上學了
About to start school again so on,
還有…
and...
我給他做早餐、午餐和晚餐
and I make his breakfast, lunch, and dinner
每天
every day.
我讓他…
I make sure he...
梳頭
combs his hair
讓他每天刷牙
and brushes his teeth every day.
教他怎麼打乒乓球
Teaching him how to play Ping-Pong.
他打得很棒
He's really good.
福雷斯 你來發球
Uh, Forrest, you go.
我們經常釣魚
We fish a lot.
我們每天晚上讀書
And every night, we read a book.
他聰明極了 珍妮
He's so smart, Jenny.
你一定會為他驕傲
You'd be so proud of him.
我會的
I am.
他還給你寫了封信
He, uh, wrote you a...a letter.
他說不許我看 我不能看
And he says I can't read it. I'm not supposed to,
所以我把它放在這兒給你
so I'll just leave it here for you.
珍妮…
Jenny...
我不知道是媽媽對
I don't know if Mama was right
還是丹中尉對
or if it...it's Lieutenant Dan.
我不知道
I don't know...
是否我們每個人都有
if we each have a...
注定的命運…
destiny...
還是我們的生命中只有偶然
or if we're all just floating around accidental-Iike
像在風中飄…
on a breeze...
但我想…
but I...I think...
也許兩者都有吧
maybe it's both.
也許兩者都在同時發生著
Maybe both get happening at the same time.
可是我想念你 珍妮
But I miss you, Jenny.
如果你想要什麼…
If there's anything you need...
我就在你身邊
I won't be far away.
你的車來了
Here's your bus.
好吧
O.K.
嗨…
Hey...
我知道
I know this.
我會在故事會上講故事
I'm gonna share that for show-and-tell
因為奶奶曾給你讀過
because Grandma used to read it to you.
我最喜歡的書
My favorite book.
好了
Here we are.
嘿…
Hey...
你該走了
here you go.
嘿 福雷斯…
Hey, Forrest...
不要…
don't...
我想告訴你我愛你
I want to tell you I love you.
我也愛你 爸爸
I love you, too, Daddy.
我就在這兒等你回來
I'll be right here when you get back.
你知道這是校車 是吧？
You understand this is the bus to school, now, don't you?
當然 你是多蘿西哈里斯 我是福雷斯甘
Of course, and you're Dorothy Harris, and I'm Forrest Gump.